<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>King Arthur, or, The British worthy a dramatick opera : perform'd at the Queens Theatre by Their Majesties servants / written by Mr. Dryden.</title>
            <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12352215</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12352215</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69869)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60031)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 208:10i or 351:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>King Arthur, or, The British worthy a dramatick opera : perform'd at the Queens Theatre by Their Majesties servants / written by Mr. Dryden.</title>
                  <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</author>
                  <author>Purcell, Henry, 1659-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jacob Tonson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Libretto only.</note>
                  <note>The music, composed by Purcell, "was never published, and it disappeared, probably within a very few years of its production"--DNB.</note>
                  <note>Sequel to Albion and Albanius, written for Charles II, who died before its performance. In 1691 it was produced, altered to the times by the omission of political overtones. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [3] at the beginning.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Worcester College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Arthur, --  King --  Drama.</term>
               <term>Operas --  Librettos.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:2"/>
            <p>King ARTHUR: OR, The Britiſh Worthy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:3"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>FInding that ſeveral of my Friends, in Buying my Plays, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Bound together, have been impos'd on by the Bookſellers foiſting in a Play which is not mine; I have here, to prevent this for the future, ſet down a Catalogue of my Plays and Poems in Quarto, putting the Plays in the Order I wrote them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Dryden.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_works">
            <list>
               <item>ESSAY on Dramatick Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etry.</item>
               <item>Wild Gallant.</item>
               <item>Rival Ladies.</item>
               <item>Indian Emperor.</item>
               <item>Maiden Queen.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Martin Marr-all.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tempeſt.</item>
               <item>Evening Love.</item>
               <item>Royal Martyr.</item>
               <item>Conqueſt of <hi>Granada,</hi> in two Parts.</item>
               <item>Marriage A-la-Mode.</item>
               <item>Love in a Nunnery.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yna.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>State of Innocence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aurenzebe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All for Love.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Limberham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oedipus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Troylus</hi> and <hi>Creſſida.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fryar.</item>
               <item>Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vindication of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Sebaſtian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Amphitryon.</item>
               <item>King <hi>Arthur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Annus Mirabilis,</hi> or, The Year of Wonders.</item>
               <item>A Poem on the Return of King <hi>Charles</hi> II.</item>
               <item>A Panegyrick on the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of King <hi>Charles</hi> II.</item>
               <item>A Poem to the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Hide.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Achitophel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Medal.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Religio Laici.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Elegy on the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> II.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Hind</hi> and <hi>Panther.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Poem on the Birth of the Prince.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:3"/>
            <p>King ARTHUR: OR, The Britiſh Worthy. A <hi>Dramatick</hi> OPERA. Perform'd at the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EENS</hi> Theatre By Their MAJESTIES Servants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by Mr.</hi> DRYDEN.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c alta Theatris</l>
               <l>Fundamenta locant: Scenis decora alta futuris.</l> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg. Aeneid. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Purpurea intexti toliunt aulaea Britanni. <bibl>
                  <hi>Georg. 3.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>— Tanton' placuit concurrere motu. <bibl>
                  <hi>Aeneid. 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Jupiter, aeternâ Genteis in pace futuras?</l>
               <l>Et Celebrare Domeſtica facta.</l> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jacob Tonſon,</hi> at the Judges-Head in <hi>Chancery-Lane</hi> near <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:4"/>
            <head>To the <hi>MARQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ISS</hi> of <hi>HALLIFAX.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My <hi>LORD,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Poem was the laſt Piece of Service, which I had the Honour to do, for my Gracious Maſter, King CHARLES the Second: And though he liv'd not to ſee the Performance of it, on the Stage; yet the PROLOGUE to it, which was the <hi>Opera</hi> of <hi>Albion</hi> and <hi>Albanius,</hi> was often practis'd before Him at <hi>Whitehal,</hi> and encourag'd by His Royal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation. It was indeed a Time, which was proper for Triumph, when He had overcome all thoſe Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties which for ſome Years had perplex'd His Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Reign: But when He had juſt reſtor'd His Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to their Senſes, and made the latter End of His Government, of a Piece with the Happy Beginning of it, He was on the ſuddain ſnatch'd away, from the Bleſſings and Acclamations of His Subjects, who arriv'd ſo late to the Knowledge of Him, that they had but juſt time enough to deſire Him longer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were to part with Him for ever. Peace be with the Aſhes of ſo Good a King! Let His Hlumane Frailties be forgotten; and His Clemency and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb facs="tcp:60031:5"/>(the inherent Virtues of His Family) be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred with a Grateful Veneration by Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, through which He ſpread the Bleſſings of them. And, as your Lordſhip held a principal Place in His Eſteem, and perhaps the firſt in His Affection, during His latter Troubles; the Succeſs which accompanied thoſe prudent Counſels, cannot but reflect an Honour on thoſe few who manag'd them; and wrought out, by their Faithfulneſs and Diligence, the Publick Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. I might dilate on the Difficulties which attended that Undertaking, the Temper of the People, the Power, Arts and Intereſt of the contrary Party, but thoſe are all of them Invidious Topicks; they are too green in our Remembrance; and he who touches on them, <hi>Incedit per ignes, ſuppoſitos cineri doloſo.</hi> But without reproaching one ſide to praiſe another, I may juſtly recommend to both, thoſe wholſom Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which wiſely adminiſtred, and as well executed, were the Means of preventing a Civil War, and of extinguiſhing a growing Fire which was juſt ready to have broken forth among us. So many Wives, who have yet their Husbands in their Arms; ſo many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who have not the Number of their Children leſſen'd; ſo many Villages, Towns and Cities, whoſe Inhabitants are not decreas'd, their Property violated, or their Wealth diminiſh'd, are yet owing to the ſober Conduct, and happy Reſults of your Advice. If a true Account may be expected by future Ages, from the preſent, your Lordſhip will be delivered over to Poſterity, in a fairer Character than I have given: And be read, not in the Preface of a Play, (whoſe Author is not vain enough to promiſe Immortality to
<pb facs="tcp:60031:5"/>others, or to hope it for himſelf) but in many Pages of a Chronicle, fill'd with Praiſes of your Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For if Writers be juſt to the Memory of King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, they cannot deny him to have been an exact Knower of Mankind, and a perfect Diſtinguiſher of their Talents. 'Tis true, his Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities often forc'd him to vary his Councellours and Councils, and ſometimes to employ ſuch Perſons in the Management of his Affairs, who were rather fit for his preſent purpoſe, than ſatisfactory to his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But where it was Choice in him, not Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he was Maſter of too much good Senſe to delight in heavy Converſation; and whatever his Favourites of State might be, yet thoſe of his Affection, were Men of Wit. He was eaſie with theſe; and comply'd only with the former: But in the latter part of his Life, which certainly requir'd to be moſt cautiouſly manag'd, his ſecret Thoughts were communicated but to few; and thoſe ſelected of that ſort, who were <hi>Amici omnium Horarum,</hi> able to adviſe him in a ſerious Conſult, where his Honour and Safety were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd; and afterwards capable of entertaining him with pleaſant Diſcourſe, as well as profitable. In this Matureſt part of his Age, when he had been long ſeaſon'd with Difficulties and Dangers, and was grown to a Niceneſs in his Choice, as being ſatisfied how few cou'd be truſted; and, of thoſe who cou'd be truſted, how few cou'd ſerve him, he confined himſelf to a ſmall Number of Boſom Friends; amongſt whom, the World is much miſtaken, if your Lordſhip was not firſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:7"/>
            <p>If the Rewards which you receiv'd for thoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, were only Honours, it rather ſhew'd the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of the Times, than any want of Kindneſs in your Royal Maſter: And as the Splendour of your Fortune ſtood not in need of being ſupported by the Crown, ſo likewiſe in being ſatisfied without other Recompence, you ſhow'd your ſelf to be above a Mercenary Intereſt; and ſtrengthen'd that Power, which beſtowed thoſe Titles on you: Which truly ſpeaking, were Marks of Acknowledgment more than Favour.</p>
            <p>But, as a Skilful Pilot will not be tempted out to Sea, in ſuſpected Weather, ſo have you wiſely choſen to withdraw your ſelf from publick Buſineſs, when the Face of Heaven grew troubled; and the frequent ſhiſting of the Winds foreſhew'd a Storm: There are Times and Seaſons when the beſt Patriots are willing to withdraw their Hands from the Commonwealth; as <hi>Phocion</hi> in his latter Days was obſerv'd to decline the Management of Affairs: Or, as <hi>Cicero,</hi> (to draw the Similitude more home) left the Pulpit, for <hi>Tuſculum;</hi> and the praiſe of Oratory, for the ſweet Enjoyments of a private Life. And, in the Happineſs of thoſe Retirements, has more oblig'd Poſterity by his <hi>Moral Precepts,</hi> than he did the Republick, in quelling the Couſpiracy of <hi>Catiline.</hi> What pru lent Man, wou'd not rather follow the Example of his Retreat, than ſtay like <hi>Cato,</hi> with a ſtubborn unſeaſonable Virtue, to oppoſe the Torrent of the People, and at laſt be driven from the Market-place by a Riot of a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, uncapable of Counſel, and deaf to Eloquence? There is likewiſe a Portion of our Lives, which every
<pb facs="tcp:60031:7"/>Wiſe Man may juſtly reſerve to his own peculiar uſe, and that without defrauding his Native Coutry. A Roman Soldier was allow'd to plead the Merit of his Services for his diſmiſſion at ſuch an Age; and there was but one Exception to that Rule, which was, an Invaſion from the <hi>Gauls.</hi> How far that, may work with your Lordſhip, I am not certain; but I hope it is not coming to the Trial.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, while the Nation is ſecur'd from Foreign Attempts, by ſo powerful a Fleet, and we enjoy not only the Happineſs, but even the Ornaments of Peace, in the Divertiſement of the Town, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer you this Trifle, which if it ſucceed upon the Stage, is like to be the chiefeſt Entertainment of our Ladies and Gentlemen this Summer. When I wrote it, ſeven Years ago, I employ'd ſome reading about it, to inform my ſelf out of <hi>Beda, Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hartus,</hi> and other Authors, concerning the Rites and Cuſtoms of the Heathen Saxons; as I alſo us'd the little Skill I have in Poetry to adorn it. But not to offend the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Times, nor a Government which has hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to protected me, I have been oblig'd ſo much to alter the firſt Deſign, and take away ſo many Beauties from the Writing, that it is now no more what it was ſormerly, than the preſent Ship of the <hi>Royal Sovereign,</hi> after ſo often taking down, and altering, to the Veſſel it was at the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. There is nothing better, than what I intended, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Muſick; which has ſince arriv'd to a greater Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in <hi>England,</hi> than ever formerly: eſpecially paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through the Artful Hands of Mr. <hi>Purcel,</hi> who has
<pb facs="tcp:60031:8"/>Compos'd it with ſo great a Genius, that he has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to fear but an ignorant, ill-judging Audience. But the Numbers of Poetry and Vocal Muſick, are ſometimes ſo contrary, that in many places I have been oblig'd to cramp my Verſes, and make them rugged to the Reader, that they may be harmonious to the Hearer: Of which I have no Reaſon to repent me, becauſe theſe ſorts of Entertainment are principally deſign'd for the Ear and Eye; and therefore in Reaſon my Art on this occaſion, ought to be ſubſervient to his And beſides, I flatter my ſelf with an Imagination that a Judicious Audience will eaſily diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Songs, wherein <hi>I</hi> have comply'd with him, and thoſe in which <hi>I</hi> have followed the Rules of Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in the Sound and Cadence of the Words. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theſe Diſadvantages, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtill remaining of the firſt Spirit with which <hi>I</hi> wrote it: And, though <hi>I</hi> can only ſpeak by gheſs, of what pleas'd my firſt and beſt Patroneſs the Dutcheſs of <hi>Monmouth</hi> in the reading, yet <hi>I</hi> will venture my Opinion, by the knowledge <hi>I</hi> have long had of her Graces Excellent Judgment, and true taſte of Poetry, that the parts of the Airy and Earthy Spirits, and that Fairy kind of writing, which depends only upon the Force of Imagination, were the Grounds of her liking the Poem, and afterwards of her Recommending it to the Queen. <hi>I</hi> have likewiſe had the ſatisfaction to hear, that Her Majeſty has Graciouſly been pleas'd to peruſe the Manuſcript of this <hi>Opera,</hi> and given it Her Royal Approbation. Poets, who ſubſiſt not but on the Favour of Sovereign Princes, and of great Perſons,
<pb facs="tcp:60031:8"/>may have leave to be a little vain, and boaſt of their Patronage, who encourage the Genius that animates them. And therefore <hi>I</hi> will again preſume to gheſs, that Her Majeſty was not diſpleas'd to find in this Poem the Praiſes of Her Native Country; and the Heroick Actions of ſo famous a Predeceſſor in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> as King <hi>Arthur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this, My Lord, <hi>I</hi> muſt conſeſs, looks with a kind of Inſinuation, that <hi>I</hi> preſent you with ſomewhat not unworthy your Protection: But <hi>I</hi> may eaſily mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake the Favour of Her Majeſty for Her Judgment: <hi>I</hi> think <hi>I</hi> cannot be deceiv'd in thus addreſſing to your Lordſhip, whom <hi>I</hi> have had the Honour to know, at that diſtance which becomes me, for ſo many Years. 'Tis true, that formerly <hi>I</hi> have ſhadow'd ſome part of your Virtues, under another Name; but the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, though ſhort and imperfect, was ſo true, that it broke through the Fable, and was diſcover'd by its Native Light. What <hi>I</hi> pretend by this Dedication, is an Honour which <hi>I</hi> do my ſelf to Poſterity, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them that <hi>I</hi> have been converſant with the firſt Perſons of the Age in which <hi>I</hi> liv'd; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by perpetuate my Proſe, when my Verſes may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be forgotten, or obſcur'd by the Fame of Future Poets. Which Ambition, amongſt my other Faults and Imperfections, be pleaſed to pardon, in</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt Obedient Servant,</hi>
John Dryden.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:60031:9"/>
            <head>Dramatis Perſonae.</head>
            <list>
               <item>KIng <hi>Arthur.</hi> — Mr. <hi>Betterton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oſwald,</hi> King of <hi>Kent,</hi> a Saxon and a Heathen. — Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conon,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> Tributary to King <hi>Arthur.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hodgſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Merlin,</hi> a famous Inchanter. — Mr. <hi>Kynaſton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oſmond,</hi> a Saxon Magician, and a Heathen. — Mr. <hi>Sandford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aurelius,</hi> Friend to <hi>Arthur.</hi> — Mr. <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Albanact,</hi> Captain of <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Guards.—Mr. <hi>Bowen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guillamar,</hi> Friend to <hi>Ofwald.</hi>—Mr. <hi>Harris.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>WOMEN.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Emmeline,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Conon.</hi>— Mrs. <hi>Bracegirdle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Matilda,</hi> her Attendant.—Mrs. <hi>Richardſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philidel,</hi> an Airy Spirit.—Mrs. <hi>Butler.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grimbald,</hi> an Earthy Spirit.—Mr. <hi>Bowman.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Officers and Soldiers, Singers and Dancers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Scene in <hi>KENT.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60031:9"/>
            <head>King ARTHUR: OR, The Britiſh Worthy.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I. SCENE I.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Conon, Aurelius, Albanact.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>THen this is the deciding Day, to fix</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great Britain</hi>'s Scepter in great <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>Or put it in the bold Invaders gripe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Oſwald,</hi> and their different Fates,</l>
                  <l>Are weighing now within the Scales of Heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>In Ten ſet Battles have we driven back</l>
                  <l>Theſe Heathen Saxons, and regain'd our Earth.</l>
                  <l>As Earth recovers from an Ebbing Tide,</l>
                  <l>Her half-drown'd Face, and lifts it o'er the Waves.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Severn</hi>'s Banks, even to this <hi>Barren-Down,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our foremoſt Men have preſt their fainty Rear,</l>
                  <l>And not one Saxon Face has been beheld;</l>
                  <l>But all their Backs, and Shoulders have been ſtuck</l>
                  <l>With foul diſhoneſt Wounds: Now here, indeed,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they have no further Ground, they ſtand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>Well have we choſe a Happy day for Fight;</l>
                  <l>For every Man, in courſe of time, has found</l>
                  <l>Some days are lucky, ſome unfortunate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:60031:10"/>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>But why this day more lucky than the reſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe this day</l>
                  <l>Is Sacred to the Patron of our Iſle;</l>
                  <l>A Chriſtian, and a Souldiers Annual Feaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, now I underſtand you, This is St. <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Cappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia</hi>'s Day.</l>
                  <l>Well, It may be ſo, but Faith I was Ignorant; we Soldiers</l>
                  <l>Seldom examine the Rubrick; and now and then a Saint may</l>
                  <l>Happen to ſlip by us; But if he be a Gentleman Saint, he will</l>
                  <l>Forgive us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oſwald,</hi> undoubtedly will Fight it bravely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>And it behoves him well, 'tis his laſt Stake.
<stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Alb.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>But what manner of Man is this <hi>Oſwald?</hi> Have ye ever ſeen him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Ne'er but once; &amp; that was to my Coſt too; I follow'd him too cloſe,</l>
                  <l>And to ſay Truth, ſomwhat Uncivilly, upon a Rout;</l>
                  <l>But he turn'd upon me, as quick and as round, as a chaft'd Boar;</l>
                  <l>And gave me two Licks acroſs the Face, to put me</l>
                  <l>In mind of my Chriſtianity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I know him well; he's free and open Hearted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>His Countries Character: That Speaks a German.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Revengeful, rugged, violently brave; and once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolv'd is never to be mov'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, he's a valiant Dog, Pox on him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>This was the Character he then maintain'd,</l>
                  <l>Whon in my Court, he ſought my Daughters Love:</l>
                  <l>My Fair, Blind, <hi>Emmeline.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot blame him for Courting the Heireſs of <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All Heireſſes are Beautiful; and as Blind as ſhe is, he would have had</l>
                  <l>No Blind Bargain of her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>For that Defeat in Love, he rais'd this War.</l>
                  <l>For Royal <hi>Arthur</hi> Reign'd within her Heart,</l>
                  <l>Ere <hi>Oſwald</hi> mov'd his Sute.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, now <hi>Aurelius,</hi> you have Nam'd a Man;</l>
                  <l>One, whom beſides the Homage that I owe,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Cornwall</hi>'s Duke, to his Imperial Crown,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd have choſen out, from all Mankind,</l>
                  <l>To be my Soveraign Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>His Worth divides him from the crowd of Kings;</l>
                  <l>So Born, without Deſert to be ſo Born;</l>
                  <l>Men, ſet aloft, to be the Scourge of Heaven;</l>
                  <l>And with long Arms, to laſh the Under-World.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60031:10"/>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arthur</hi> is all that's Excellent in <hi>Oſwald;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And void of all his Faults: In Battle brave;</l>
                  <l>But ſtill Serene in all the Stormy War,</l>
                  <l>Like Heaven above the Clouds; and after Fight,</l>
                  <l>As Merciful and Kind, to vanquiſht Foes,</l>
                  <l>As a Forgiving God; but ſee, he's here,</l>
                  <l>And Praiſe is Dumb before him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter King</hi> Arthur, <hi>Reading a Letter, with Attendants.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arthur Reading.</speaker>
                  <l>Go on, Auſpicious Prince, the Stars are kind:</l>
                  <l>Unfold thy Banners to the willing Wind;</l>
                  <l>While I, with Aiery Legions, help thy Arms;</l>
                  <l>Confronting Art with Art, and Charms with Charms.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Merlin</hi> writes; nor can we doubt th' event,
<stage>
                        <hi>To</hi> Con.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>With Heav'n and you to Friends; Oh Noble <hi>Conon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You taught my tender Hands the Trade of War;</l>
                  <l>And now again you Helm your hoary Head,</l>
                  <l>And under double weight of Age and Arms,</l>
                  <l>Aſſert your Countries Freedom, and my Crown.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, my Son.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt happy in that Name!</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>Emmeline,</hi> to <hi>Oſwald</hi>'s Vows reſus'd,</l>
                  <l>You made my plighted Bride:</l>
                  <l>Your Charming Daughter, who like Love, Born Blind,</l>
                  <l>Un-aiming hits, with ſureſt Archery,</l>
                  <l>And Innocently kills.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Remember, Son,</l>
                  <l>You are a General, other Wars require you.</l>
                  <l>For ſee the <hi>Saxon</hi> Groſs begins to move.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Their Infantry Embattel'd, ſquare and cloſe,</l>
                  <l>March firmly on, to fill the middle ſpace:</l>
                  <l>Cover'd by their advancing Cavalry.</l>
                  <l>By Heav'n, 'tis Beauteous Horrour:</l>
                  <l>The Noble <hi>Oſwald</hi> has provok'd my Envy.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Emmeline, <hi>led by</hi> Matilda.</stage>
                  <l>Ha! Now my Beauteous <hi>Emmeline</hi> appears</l>
                  <l>Anew, but Oh, a ſofter Flame, inſpires me:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60031:11"/>
Even Rage and Vengeance, ſlumber at her ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſte your Farewel; I'll chear my Troops, and wait ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Conon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Father, Father, I am ſure you're here;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I ſee your Voice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>No, thou miſtak'ſt thy hearing for thy ſight;</l>
                  <l>He's gone, my <hi>Emmeline;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And I but ſtay to gaze on thoſe fair Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Which cannot view the Conqueſt they have made.</l>
                  <l>Oh Star-like Night, dark only to thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>But full of Glory, as thoſe Lamps of Heav'n</l>
                  <l>That ſee not, when they ſhine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>What is this Heav'n, and Stars, and Night, and Day,</l>
                  <l>To which you thus compare my Eyes and me?</l>
                  <l>I underſtand you, when you ſay you love:</l>
                  <l>For, when my Father claſps my Hand in his,</l>
                  <l>That's cold, and I can feel it hard and wrinkl'd;</l>
                  <l>But when you graſp it, then I ſigh and pant,</l>
                  <l>And ſomething ſmarts, and tickles at my Heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Artleſs Love! where the Soul moves the Tongue,</l>
                  <l>And only Nature ſpeaks what Nature thinks!</l>
                  <l>Had ſhe but Eyes!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Juſt now you ſaid I had:</l>
                  <l>I ſee 'em, I have two.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>But neither ſee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm ſure they hear you then:</l>
                  <l>What can your Eyes do more?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>They view your Beauties.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not I ſee? You have a Face, like mine,</l>
                  <l>Two Hands, and two round, pretty, riſing Breaſts,</l>
                  <l>That heave like mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>But you deſcribe a Woman.</l>
                  <l>Nor is it ſight, but touching with your Hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Then 'tis my Hand that ſees, and that's all one:</l>
                  <l>For is not ſeeing, touching with your Eyes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>No, for I ſee at diſtance, where I touch not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>If you can ſee ſo far, and yet not touch,</l>
                  <l>I fear you ſee my Naked Legs and Feet</l>
                  <l>Quite through my Cloaths; pray do not ſee ſo well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Fear not, ſweet Innocence;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60031:11"/>
I view the lovely Features of your Face;</l>
                  <l>Your Lips Carnation, your dark ſhaded Eye-brows,</l>
                  <l>Black Eyes, And Snow white Forehead; all the Colours</l>
                  <l>That make your Beauty, and produce my Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, then, you do not love on equal terms:</l>
                  <l>I love you dearly, without all theſe helps:</l>
                  <l>I cannot ſee your Lips Carnation,</l>
                  <l>Your ſhaded Eye-brows, nor your Milk-white Eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſtill miſtake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed I thought you had a Noſe and Eyes,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a Face as mine; have not Men Faces?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, none like yours, ſo excellently fair.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Then wou'd I had no Face; for I wou'd be Juſt ſuch a one as you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, 'tis vain to inſtruct your Innocence,</l>
                  <l>You have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Light or Colours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Emm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Why, is not that a Trumpet?
<stage>Trumpet ſound within.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>I knew it.</l>
                  <l>And I can tell you how the ſound on't looks:</l>
                  <l>It looks as if it had an angry fighting Face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis now indeed a ſharp unpleaſant ſound,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it calls me hence, from her I love,</l>
                  <l>To meet Ten thouſand Foes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>How does ſo many Men ee'r come to meet?</l>
                  <l>This Devil Trumpet vexes 'em, and then</l>
                  <l>They feel about, for one anothers Faces;</l>
                  <l>And ſo they meet, and kill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll tell ye all, when we have gain'd the Field;</l>
                  <l>One kiſs of your fair Hand, the pledge of Conqueſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſo a ſhort farewel.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Kiſſes her Hand, and</hi> Exit <hi>with</hi> Aurel. Alb. <hi>and Attendants.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>My Heart, and Vows, go with him to the Fight:</l>
                  <l>May every Foe, be that, which they call blind,</l>
                  <l>And none of all their Swords have Eyes to find him.</l>
                  <l>But lead me nearer to the Trumpet's Face;</l>
                  <l>For that brave Sound upholds my ſainting Heart;</l>
                  <l>And while I hear, methinks I ſight my part.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit, led by</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60031:12"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Oſwald <hi>and</hi> Oſmond.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>The Scene repreſents a place of Heathen worſhip; The three Saxon Gods,</hi> Woden, Thor, <hi>and</hi> Freya <hi>placed on Pedeſtals. An Altar.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis time to haſten our myſterious Rites;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe your Army waits you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Oſwald <hi>making three Bows before the three Images.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thor, Freya, Woden,</hi> all ye Saxon Powers,</l>
                  <l>Hear and revenge my Father <hi>Hengiſt</hi>'s death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>Father of Gods and Men, great <hi>Woden,</hi> hear.</l>
                  <l>Mount thy hot Courfer, drive amidſt thy Foes;</l>
                  <l>Liſt high thy thund'ring Arm, let every blow</l>
                  <l>Daſh out a miſ-believing Briton's Brains.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Father of Gods and Men, great <hi>Woden</hi> hear;</l>
                  <l>Give Conqueſt to thy Saxon Race, and me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thor, Freya, Woden,</hi> hear, and ſpell your Saxons,</l>
                  <l>With Sacred Runick Rhimes, from Death in Battle.</l>
                  <l>Edge their bright Swords, and blunt the Britons Darts.</l>
                  <l>No more, Great Prince, for ſee my truſty Fiend,</l>
                  <l>Who all the Night has wing'd the dusky Air.</l>
                  <l>Grimbald, <hi>a fierce earthy Spirit ariſes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What news, my <hi>Grimbald?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>I have plaid my part;</l>
                  <l>For I have Steel'd the Fools that are to dye;</l>
                  <l>Six Fools, ſo prodigal of Life and Soul,</l>
                  <l>That, for their Country, they devote their Lives</l>
                  <l>A Sacrifice to Mother Earth, and <hi>Woden.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis well; But are we ſure of Victory?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ask'ſt thou me?</l>
                  <l>Inſpect their Intrails, draw from thence thy Gueſs:</l>
                  <l>Bloud we muſt have, without it we are dumb.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>Say, Where's thy fellow-ſervant, <hi>Philidel?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Why comes not he?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>For, he's a puleing Sprite.</l>
                  <l>Why didſt thou chuſe a tender airy Form,</l>
                  <l>Unequal to the mighty work of Miſchief;</l>
                  <l>His Make is flitting, ſoft, and yielding Atomes:</l>
                  <l>He trembles at the yawning gulph of Hell,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> dares approach the Flame, leſt he ſhou'd ſinge</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>audy ſilken Wings.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60031:12"/>
He ſighs when he ſhould plunge a Soul in Sulphur,</l>
                  <l>As with Compaſſion, touch'd of fooliſh man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>What a half Devil's he?</l>
                  <l>His Errand was, to draw the Low-land damps,</l>
                  <l>And Noiſom vapours, from the ſoggy Fens:</l>
                  <l>Then, breath the baleful ſtench, with all his force,</l>
                  <l>Full on the faces of our Chriſtned Foes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>Accordingly he drein'd thoſe Marſhy-grounds;</l>
                  <l>And bagg'd 'em in a blue peſtiferous Cloud;</l>
                  <l>Which when he ſhou'd have blown, the frighted Elſ.</l>
                  <l>Eſpy'd the Red Croſs Banners of their Hoſt;</l>
                  <l>And ſaid he durſt not add to his damnation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>I'le puniſh him at leiſure;</l>
                  <l>Call in the Victims to propitiate Hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>That's my kind Maſter, I ſhall break faſt on 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Grimbald <hi>goes to the Door, and Re-enters with 6 Saxons in White, with Swords in their hands. They range themſelves 3 and 3 in oppoſition to each other.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>The reſt of the Stage is fill'd with Prieſts and Singers.</stage>
               <l>WOden, <hi>firſt to thee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Milk white Steed, in Battle won;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We have Sacrific'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                  <hi>VVe have Sacrific'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Verſ.</stage> 
                  <hi>Let our next Oblation be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> Thor, <hi>thy thundring Son,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of ſuch another.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                  <hi>We have Sacrific'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Verſ.</stage> 
                  <hi>A third;</hi> (<hi>of</hi> Friezeland <hi>breed was he,</hi>)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> Woden<hi>'s Wife, and to</hi> Thor<hi>'s Mother:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And now we have atton'd all three</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We have Sacrific'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                  <hi>VVe have Sacrific'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60031:13"/>
                  <stage>2 Voc.</stage> 
                  <hi>The VVhite Horſe Neigh'd aloud.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> VVoden <hi>thanks we render.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> VVoden, <hi>we have vow'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                  <hi>To</hi> VVoden, <hi>our Defender.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>The four laſt Lines in <hi>CHORUS.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>
                  <stage>Verſ.</stage> 
                  <hi>The Lot is Caſt, and</hi> Tanfan <hi>pleas'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                  <hi>Of Mortal Cares you ſhall be eas'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brave Souls to be renown'd in Story.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Honour prizing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death deſpiſing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fame acquiring</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By Expiring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dye, and reap the fruit of Glory.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brave Souls to be renown'd in Story.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Verſ.</stage> 2. <hi>I call ye all,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> VVoden<hi>'s Hall;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your Temples round</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVith Ivy bound,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Goblets Crown'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And plenteous Bowls of burniſh'd Gold;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVhere you ſhall Laugh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And dance and quaff,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Juice, that makes the Britons bold.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>The ſix Saxons are led off by the Prieſts, in Order to be Sacrific'd.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Owſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Ambitious Fools we are,</l>
                  <l>And yet Ambition is a Godlike Fault:</l>
                  <l>Or rather, 'tis no Fault in Souls Born great,</l>
                  <l>Who dare extend their Glory by their Deeds.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Britany</hi> prepare to change thy State,</l>
                  <l>And from this Day begin thy Saxon date.</l>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60031:13"/>
A Battle ſuppoſed to be given behind the Scenes, with Drums, Trumpets, and Military Shouts and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions: After which, the <hi>Britons,</hi> expreſſing their Joy for the Victory, ſing this Song of Triumph.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>COme if you dare, our Trumpets ſound;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come if you dare, the Faes rebound:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We come, we come, we come, we come,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Says the double, double, double Beat of the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Drum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now they charge on amain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now they rally again:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Gods from above the Mad Labour behold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And pity Mankind that will periſh for Gold.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Fainting</hi> Saxons <hi>quit their Ground,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their Trumpets Languiſh in the Sound;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They fly, they fly, they fly, they fly;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Victoria, Victoria, <hi>the Bold</hi> Britons <hi>cry.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now the Victory's won,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To the Plunder we run:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We return to our Laſſes like Fortunate Traders,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Triumphant with Spoils of the Vanquiſh'd Invaders.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60031:14"/>
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Philidel.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>ALas, for pity, of this bloody Field!</l>
                  <l>Piteous it needs muſt be, when I, a Spirit,</l>
                  <l>Can have ſo ſoft a ſenſe of Humane Woes!</l>
                  <l>Ah! for ſo many Souls, as but this Morn'</l>
                  <l>Were cloath'd with Fleſh, and warm'd with Vital Blood,</l>
                  <l>But naked now, or ſhirted but with Air.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Merlin, <hi>with Spirits, deſcends to</hi> Philidel, <hi>on a Chariot drawn by Dragons.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>What art thou, Spirit, of what Name and Order?</l>
                  <l>(For I have view'd thee in my Magick Glaſs,)</l>
                  <l>Making thy moan, among the Midnight Wolves,</l>
                  <l>That Bay the ſilent Moon: Speak, I Conjure thee,</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Merlin</hi> bids thee, at whoſe awful Wand,</l>
                  <l>The pale Ghoſt quivers, and the grim Fiend gaſps.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>An Airy Shape, the tender'ſt of my kind,</l>
                  <l>The laſt ſeduc'd, and leaſt deform'd of Hell;</l>
                  <l>Half white, and ſhuffl'd in the Crowd, I fell;</l>
                  <l>Deſirous to repent, and loth to ſin,</l>
                  <l>Awkward in Miſchief, piteous of Mankind,</l>
                  <l>My Name is <hi>Philidel,</hi> my Lot in Air,</l>
                  <l>Where next beneath the Moon, and neareſt Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>I ſoar; and have a Glimpſe to be receiv'd,</l>
                  <l>For which the ſwarthy <hi>Daemons</hi> envy me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Buſineſs here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſhun the Saxon Wizards dire Commands,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oſmend,</hi> the awful'ſt Name next thine below,</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe I refus'd to hurl a Noyſom Fog</l>
                  <l>On Chriſten'd Heads, the Hue and Cry of Hell</l>
                  <l>Is rais'd againſt me, for a Fugitive Spright.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oſmond</hi> ſhall know, a greater Power protects thee;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60031:14"/>
But follow thou the Whiſpers of thy Soul,</l>
                  <l>That draw thee nearer Heav'n.</l>
                  <l>And, as thy place is neareſt to the Sky,</l>
                  <l>The Rays will reach thee firſt, and bleach thy Soot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>In hope of that, I ſpread my Azure Wings,</l>
                  <l>And wiſhing ſtill, for yet I dare not pray,</l>
                  <l>I bask in Day-light, and behold with Joy</l>
                  <l>My Scum work outward, and my Ruſt wear off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, 'tis my hopeful Devil; now mark me, <hi>Philidel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will employ thee, for thy future Good:</l>
                  <l>Thou know'ſt, in ſpite of Valiant <hi>Oſwald</hi>'s Arms,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Oſmond</hi>'s Powerful Spells, the Field is ours. —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Maſter! haſten</l>
                  <l>Thy Dread Commands; for <hi>Grimbald</hi> is at Hand;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oſmond</hi>'s fierce Fiend, I ſnuff his Earthy Scent:</l>
                  <l>The Conquering <hi>Britons,</hi> he miſleads to Rivers,</l>
                  <l>Or dreadful Downfalls of unheeded Rocks;</l>
                  <l>Where many fall, that ne'er ſhall riſe again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Be that thy care, to ſtand by falls of Brooks,</l>
                  <l>And trembling Bogs, that bear a Green-Sword ſhow.</l>
                  <l>Warn off the bold Purſuers from the Chace:</l>
                  <l>No more, they come, and we divide the Task.</l>
                  <l>But leſt fierce <hi>Grimbala</hi>'s pond'rous Bulk oppreſs</l>
                  <l>Thy tender flitting Air, I'll leave my Band</l>
                  <l>Of Spirits with United Strength to Aid thee,</l>
                  <l>And Force with Force repel.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Merlin <hi>on his Chariot.</hi> Merlin<hi>'s Spirits ſtay with</hi> Philidel.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Grimbald <hi>in the Habit of a Shepherd, follow'd by King</hi> Arthur, Conon, Aurelius, Albanact <hi>and Soldiers, who wander at a diſtance in the Scenes.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, this way, <hi>Britons,</hi> follow <hi>Oſwald</hi>'s flight;</l>
                  <l>This Evening as I whiſtl'd out my Dog,</l>
                  <l>To drive my ſtraggling Flock, and pitch'd my Fold,</l>
                  <l>I ſaw him dropping Sweat, o'er labour'd, ſtiff,</l>
                  <l>Make faintly as he could, to yonder Dell.</l>
                  <l>Tread in my Steps; long Neighbourhood by Day</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60031:15"/>
Has made theſe Fields familiar in the Night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank thee, Shepherd;</l>
                  <l>Expect Reward, lead on, we follow thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Phil. ſings.</stage> 
                     <hi>Hither this way, this way bend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Truſt not that Malicious Fiend:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thoſe are falſe deluding Lights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wafted far and near by Sprights.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Truſt 'em not, for they'll deceive ye;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And in Bogs and Marſhes leave ye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor. of Phil. Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Hither this way, this way bend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor. of Grimb. Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>This way, this way bend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Phil. ſings.</stage> 
                     <hi>If you ſtep, no Danger thinking,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Down you fall, a Furlong ſinking:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis a Fiend who has annoy'd ye;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Name but Heav'n, and he'll avoid ye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor. of Phil. Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Hither this way, this way bend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor. of Grimb. Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>This way, this way bend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Philidels Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Truſt not that Malicious Fiend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Grimbalds Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Truſt me, I am no Malicious Fiend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Philidels Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Hither this way,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Some wicked Phantom, Foe to Human kind,</l>
                  <l>Miſguides our Steps.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alba.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll follow him no farther.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimbald ſpeaks.</speaker>
                  <l>By Hell ſhe ſings 'em back, in my deſpight.</l>
                  <l>I had a Voice in Heav'n, ere Sulph'rous Steams.</l>
                  <l>Had damp'd it to a hoarſeneſs; but I'll try.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60031:15"/>
                     <l>
                        <stage>He ſings.</stage> 
                        <hi>Let not a Moon-born Elf miſlead ye,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From your Prey, and from your Glory.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Too far, Alas, he has betray'd ye:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Follow the Flames, that wave before ye:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sometimes ſev'n, and ſometimes one;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hurry, hurry, hurry, hurry on.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>See, ſee, the Footſteps plain appearing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That way</hi> Oſwald <hi>choſe for flying:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Firm is the Turff, and fit for bearing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where yonder Pearly Dews are lying.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Far he cannot hence be gone;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hurry, hurry, hurry, hurry on.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true, he ſays; the Footſteps yet are freſh</l>
                  <l>Upon the Sod, no falling Dew-Drops have</l>
                  <l>Diſturb'd the Print.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>All are going to follow</hi> Grimbald.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Philidel ſings.</stage> 
                     <hi>Hither this way.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor. of Phil. Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Hither this way, this way bend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor. of Grimb. Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>This way, this way bend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Philidels Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Truſt not that Malicious Fiend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Grimb. Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Truſt me, I am no Malicious Fiend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Philidels Spirits.</stage> 
                     <hi>Hither this way,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>They all incline to</hi> Philidel.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60031:16"/>
                  <stage>Grim. ſpeaks.</stage>
                  <l>Curſe on her Voice, I muſt my Prey forego;</l>
                  <l>Thou, <hi>Philidel,</hi> ſhalt anſwer this, below.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Grimbald <hi>ſinks with a Flaſh.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>At laſt the Cheat is plain;</l>
                  <l>The Cloven-footed Fiend is Vaniſh'd from us;</l>
                  <l>Good Angels be our Guides, and bring us back.</l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Phil. ſinging.</stage> 
                     <hi>Come follow, follow, follow me.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                     <hi>Come follow,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And me. And me. And me. And me.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Verſ. 2 Voc.</stage> 
                     <hi>And Green-Sword all your way ſhall be.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                     <hi>Come follow,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Verſ.</stage> 
                     <hi>No</hi> Goblin <hi>or</hi> Elf <hi>ſhall dare to offend ye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                     <hi>No, no, no,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No</hi> Goblin <hi>or</hi> Elf <hi>ſhall dare to offend ye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Verſ. 3 Voc.</stage> 
                     <hi>VVe Brethren of Air,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You</hi> Hero<hi>'s will bear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To the Kind and the Fair that attend ye.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                     <hi>VVe Brethren,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Philidel <hi>and the Spirits go off ſinging, with King</hi> Arthur <hi>and the reſt in the middle of them.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Emmeline <hi>led by</hi> Matilda. <hi>Pavilicn Scene.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>No News of my Dear Love, or of my Father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>None, Madam, ſince the gaining of the Battel;</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Arthur</hi> is a Royal Conqueror now,</l>
                  <l>And well deſerves your Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>But now I fear</l>
                  <l>He'll be too great, to love poor ſilly me.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60031:16"/>
If he be dead, or never come agen,</l>
                  <l>I mean to die: But there's a greater doubt,</l>
                  <l>Since I ne'er ſaw him here,</l>
                  <l>How ſhall I meet him in another World?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>I have heard ſomething, how two Bodies meet,</l>
                  <l>But how Souls joyn, I know not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhou'd find him,</l>
                  <l>For ſurely I have ſeen him in my Sleep,</l>
                  <l>And then, methought, he put his Mouth to mine,</l>
                  <l>And eat a thouſand Kiſſes on my Lips;</l>
                  <l>Sure by his Kiſſing I cou'd find him out</l>
                  <l>Among a thouſand Angels in the Sky.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>But what a kind of Man do you ſuppoſe him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>He muſt be made of the moſt precious things:</l>
                  <l>And I believe his Mouth, and Eyes, and Cheeks,</l>
                  <l>And Noſe, and all his Face, are made of Gold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Heav'n bleſs us, Madam, what a Face you make him.</l>
                  <l>If it be yellow, he muſt have the Jaundies,</l>
                  <l>And that's a bad Diſeaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then do Lovers give a thing ſo bad</l>
                  <l>As Gold, to Women, whom ſo well they love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe that bad thing, Gold, buys all good things.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet I muſt know him better: Of all Colours,</l>
                  <l>Tell me which is the pureſt, and the ſofteſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſay 'tis Black.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then, ſince Gold is hard, and yet is precious,</l>
                  <l>His Face muſt all be made of ſoft, black Gold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>But, Madam —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>No more; I have learn'd enough for once.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Here are a Crew of Kentiſh Lads and Laſſes.</l>
                  <l>Wou'd entertain ye, till your Lord's return,</l>
                  <l>With Songs and Dances, to divert your Cares.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>O bring 'em in,</l>
                  <l>For tho' I cannot ſee the Songs, I love 'em;</l>
                  <l>And Love, they tell me, is a Dance of Hearts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60031:17"/>
                  <stage>Enter Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <stage>1 Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd ſings.</stage> 
                     <hi>How bleſt are Shepherds, how happy their Laſſes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>1 Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd ſings.</stage> 
                     <hi>While Drums &amp; Trumpets are ſounding Alarms!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>1 Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd ſings.</stage> 
                     <hi>Over our Lowly Sheds all the Storm paſſes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And when we die, 'tis in each others Arms.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All the Day on our Herds, and Flocks employing;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All the Night on our Flutes, and in enjoying.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                     <hi>All the Day,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bright Nymphs of</hi> Britain, <hi>with Graces attended,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let not your Days without Pleaſure expire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Honour's but empty, and when Youth is ended,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All Men will praiſe you, but none will deſire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let not Youth fly away without Contenting;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Age will come time enough, for your Repenting.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                        <hi>Let not Youth,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Here the Men offer their Flutes to the Women, which they refuſe.</stage>
               <l>
                  <stage>2 Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſ.</stage> 
                  <hi>Shepherd, Shepherd, leave Decoying,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>2 Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſ.</stage> 
                  <hi>Pipes are ſweet, a Summers Day;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But a little after Toying,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Women have the Shot to Pay.</hi>
               </l>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here are Marriage-Vows for ſigning,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Set their Marks that cannot write:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>After that, witghout Repining,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Play and Welcom, Day and Night.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Here the Women give the Men Contracts, which they accept.</stage>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60031:17"/>
                  <stage>Chor. of all.</stage> 
                  <hi>Come, Shepherds, lead up, a lively Meaſure;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <stage>Chor. of all.</stage> 
                  <hi>The Cares of VVedlock, are Cares of Pleaſure:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But whether Marriage bring Joy, or Sorrow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Make ſure of this Day, and hang to Morrow.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>The Dance after the Song, and</hi> Exeunt <hi>Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter on the other ſide of the Stage,</hi> Oſwald <hi>and</hi> Guillamar.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſw.</speaker>
                  <l>The Night has wilder'd us; and we are faln</l>
                  <l>Among their foremoſt Tents.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Guill.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! What are theſe!</l>
                  <l>They ſeem of more than Vulgar Quality.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>What Sounds are thoſe? They cannot far be diſtant:</l>
                  <l>Where are we now, <hi>Matilda?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Juſt before your Tent:</l>
                  <l>Fear not, they muſt be Friends, and they approach.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>My <hi>Arthur,</hi> ſpeak, my Love; Are you return'd</l>
                  <l>To bleſs your <hi>Emmeline?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa. to Guilla.</speaker>
                  <l>I know that Face:</l>
                  <l>'Tis my Ungrateful Fair, who, ſcorning mine,</l>
                  <l>Accepts my Rivals Love: Heav'n, thou'rt bounteous,</l>
                  <l>Thou ow'ſt me nothing now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Fear grows upon me:</l>
                  <l>Speak what you are; ſpeak, or I call for help.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>We are your Guards.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah me! We are betray'd; 'tis <hi>Oſwala</hi>'s Voice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Let 'em not ſee our Voices, and then they cannot find us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſw.</speaker>
                  <l>Paſſions in Men Oppreſs'd, are doubly ſtrong.</l>
                  <l>I take her from King <hi>Arthur;</hi> there's Revenge:</l>
                  <l>If ſhe can love, ſhe buoys my ſinking Portunes:</l>
                  <l>Good Reaſons both: I'll on.—Fear nothing, Ladies,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall be ſafe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Oſwald and Guillamar ſerve Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meline and Matilda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em. &amp; Matil.</speaker>
                  <l>Help, help; a Rape, a Rape!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>By Heav'n ye injure me, thô Perce is us'd,</l>
                  <l>Your Honour ſhall be ſacred.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Help, help, Oh <hi>Britons. help!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Your <hi>Britons</hi> cannot help you:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60031:18"/>
This Arm, through all their Troops, ſhall force my way;</l>
                  <l>Yet neither quit my Honour, nor my Prey.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt, the Women ſtill crying.</stage>
               <stage>An Alarm within: Some Soldiers running over the Stage: Follow, follow, follow.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Albanact <hi>Captain of the Guurds, with Soldiers.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Which way went th' Alarm?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Sol.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Here, towards the Caſtle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Pox o' this Victory; the whole Camp's debauch'd:</l>
                  <l>All Drunk or Whoring: This way, follow, follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>The Alarm renews: Claſhing of Swords within for a while.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Re-enter</hi> Albanact, <hi>Officer and Soldiers.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Officer.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſits the Conqueſt on great <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Brow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alba.</speaker>
                  <l>As when the Lover, with the King is mixt,</l>
                  <l>He puts the gain of <hi>Britain</hi> in a Scale,</l>
                  <l>Which weighing with the loſs of <hi>Emmeline,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He thinks he's ſcarce a Saver.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Strumpet within.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Officer.</speaker>
                  <l>Hark! a Trumpet!</l>
                  <l>It ſounds a Parley.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alba.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis from <hi>Oſwald</hi> then,</l>
                  <l>An Eccho to King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s Friendly Summons,</l>
                  <l>Sent ſince he heard the Rape of <hi>Emmeline,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ask an Interview.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Trumpet anſwering on the other ſide.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Officer.</speaker>
                  <l>But hark! already</l>
                  <l>Our Trumpet makes reply; and ſee both preſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Arthur <hi>on one ſide attended,</hi> Oſwald <hi>on the other with Attendants, and</hi> Guillamar. <hi>They meet and ſalute.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arthur.</speaker>
                  <l>Brave <hi>Oſwald!</hi> We have met on Friendlier Terms,</l>
                  <l>Companions of a War, with Common Intereſt</l>
                  <l>Againſt the Bordering <hi>Picts:</hi> But Times are chang'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60031:18"/>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>If ſo we meet not now, the fault's your own;</l>
                  <l>For you have wrong'd me much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh you wou'd tell me,</l>
                  <l>I call'd more <hi>Saxons</hi> in, t' enlarge my Bounds:</l>
                  <l>If thoſe be Wrongs, the War has well redreſs'd ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Miſtake me not, I count not War a Wrong:</l>
                  <l>War is the Trade of Kings, that fight for Empire;</l>
                  <l>And better be a Lyon, than a Sheep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>In what, then, have I wrong'd ye?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>In my Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Even Love's an Empire too; The Noble Soul,</l>
                  <l>Like Kings, is Covetous of ſingle Sway.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>I blame ye not, for loving <hi>Emmeline:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſince the Soul is free, and Love is choice,</l>
                  <l>You ſhou'd have made a Conqueſt of her Mind,</l>
                  <l>And not have forc'd her Perſon by a Rape.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Whether by Force, or Stratagem, we gain;</l>
                  <l>Still Gaining is our End, in War or Love.</l>
                  <l>Her Mind's the Jewel, in her Body lock'd;</l>
                  <l>If I would gain the Gem, and want the Key,</l>
                  <l>It follows I muſt ſeize the Cabinet:</l>
                  <l>But to ſecure your fear, her Honour is untouch'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Was Honour ever ſafe in Brutal Hands?</l>
                  <l>So ſafe are Lambs within the Lyons Paw;</l>
                  <l>Ungrip'd and plaid with, till fierce Hunger calls,</l>
                  <l>Then Nature ſhews it ſelf; the cloſe-hid Nails</l>
                  <l>Are ſtretch'd, and open'd, to the panting Prey.</l>
                  <l>But if indeed, you are ſo Cold a Lover —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Not Cold, but Honourable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Then Reſtore her.</l>
                  <l>That done, I ſhall believe you Honourable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Think'ſt thou I will forego a Victor's Right?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Say rather, of an Impious Raviſher.</l>
                  <l>That Caſtle, were it wall'd with Adamant,</l>
                  <l>Can hide thy Head, but till to Morrow's Dawn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>And ere to Morrow, I may be a God,</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Emmeline</hi> be kind: But kind or cruel,</l>
                  <l>I tell thee, <hi>Arthur,</hi> but to ſee this Day,</l>
                  <l>That Heavenly Face, tho' not to have her mine,</l>
                  <l>I would give up a hundred Years of Life,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60031:19"/>
And bid Fate cut to Morrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſoon will come, and thou repent too late;</l>
                  <l>Which to prevent, I'll bribe thee to be honeſt.</l>
                  <l>Thy Noble Head, accuſtom'd to a Crown,</l>
                  <l>Shall wear it ſtill: Nor ſhall thy Hand forget</l>
                  <l>The Sceptre's uſe: From <hi>Medway</hi>'s pleaſing Stream,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Severn</hi>'s Roar, be thine.</l>
                  <l>In ſhort, Reſtore my Love, and ſhare my Kingdom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Not, tho' you ſpread my Sway from <hi>Thames</hi> to <hi>Tyber;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such Gifts might bribe a King, but not a Lover.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Then prithee give me back my Kingly Word,</l>
                  <l>Paſs'd for thy ſafe return; and let this Hour,</l>
                  <l>In ſingle Combat, Hand to Hand, decide</l>
                  <l>The Fate of Empire, and of <hi>Emmeline.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Not, that I fear, do I decline this Combat;</l>
                  <l>And not decline it neither, but defer:</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Emmeline</hi> has been my Prize as long</l>
                  <l>As ſhe was thine, I dare thee to the Duel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>I nam'd your utmoſt Term of Life; To Morrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>You are not Fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>But Fate is in this Arm.</l>
                  <l>You might have made a Merit of your Theft.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! Theft! Your Guards can tell, I ſtole her not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Had I been preſent—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>Had you been preſent, ſhe had been mine more Nobly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>There lies your way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>My way lies where I pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>Expect (for <hi>Oſwald</hi>'s Magick cannot fail)</l>
                  <l>A long To Morrow, ere your Arms prevail:</l>
                  <l>Or if I fall, make Room ye bleſt above,</l>
                  <l>For one who was undone, and dy'd for Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Oſwald and his Party.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>There may be one black Minute ere To Morrow:</l>
                  <l>For who can tell, what Pow'r, and Luſt, and Charms,</l>
                  <l>May do this Night? To Arms, with ſpeed, to Arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60031:19"/>
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Arthur, Conon <hi>and</hi> Aurelius.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>FUrle up our Colours, and Unbrace our Drums;</l>
                  <l>Diſlodge betimes; and quit this fatal Coaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Have we forgot to Conquer?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
                  <l>Caſt off Hope:</l>
                  <l>Th' Imbattl'd Legions of Fire, Air, and Earth,</l>
                  <l>Are banded for our Foes.</l>
                  <l>For going to diſcover, with the Dawn,</l>
                  <l>You Southern Hill, which promis'd to the Sight</l>
                  <l>A Riſe more eaſie to attack the Fort,</l>
                  <l>Scarce had we ſtept on the Forbidden Ground,</l>
                  <l>When the Woods ſhook, the Trees ſtood briſtling up;</l>
                  <l>A Living Trembling Nodded through the Leaves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Poplars, and Aſpen-Boughs, a Pannick Fright.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Poplars, and Aſpen-Boughs, a Pannick Fright.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conon.</speaker>
                  <l>We thought ſo too, and doubled ſtill our pace.</l>
                  <l>But ſtrait a rumbling Sound, like bellowing Winds,</l>
                  <l>Roſe and grew loud; Confus'd with Howls of Wolves,</l>
                  <l>And Grunts of Bears; and dreadful Hiſs of Snakes;</l>
                  <l>Shreiks more than Humane; Globes of Hail pour'd down</l>
                  <l>An Armed Winter, and Inverted Day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Dreadful indeed!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>Count then our Labour's loſt:</l>
                  <l>For otherway lies none, to mount the Cliff,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs we borrow Wings, and ſail thro' Air.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Uperceive a Danger worthy me.</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Oſmond</hi>'s Work, a Band of Hell-hir'd Slaves;</l>
                  <l>Be mine the Hazard, mine ſhall be the Fame.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Arthur <hi>is going out, but is met by</hi> Merlin, <hi>Who takes him by the Hand, and brings him back.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60031:20"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Merlin.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, Sir, and wait Heav'ns time; th' Attempts too dangerous:</l>
                  <l>There's not a Tree in that Inchanted Grove,</l>
                  <l>But numbred out, and given by tale to Fiends;</l>
                  <l>And under every Leaf a Spirit couch'd.</l>
                  <l>But by what Method to diſſolve theſe Charms,</l>
                  <l>Is yet unknown to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Hadſt thou been here, (for what can what thy Skill?)</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Emmeline</hi> had been the boaſt of <hi>Oſwald;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor I fore-warn'd, been wanting to her Guard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Her darkn'd Eyes had ſeen the Light of Heav'n;</l>
                  <l>That was thy promiſe too, and this the time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor has my Aid been abſent, tho' unſeen,</l>
                  <l>With Friendly Guides in your benighted Maze.</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Emmeline</hi> ſhall longer want the Sun.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Is there an end of Woes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>There is, and ſudden.</l>
                  <l>I have employ'd a ſubtil Airy Spright</l>
                  <l>T' explore the paſſage, and prepare my way.</l>
                  <l>My ſelf, mean time, will view the Magick Wood,</l>
                  <l>To learn whereon depends its Force.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>But <hi>Emmeline</hi> —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Fear not: This Vial ſhall reſtore her ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh might I hope (and what's impoſſible</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Merlin</hi>'s Art) to be my ſelf the Bearer,</l>
                  <l>That with the Light of Heav'n ſhe may diſcern</l>
                  <l>Her Lover firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis wondrous hazardous;</l>
                  <l>Yet I foreſee th' Event, 'tis fortunate.</l>
                  <l>I'll bear ye ſafe, and bring ye back unharm'd:</l>
                  <l>Then loſe not precious Time, but follow me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt Omnes,</hi> Merlin <hi>leading</hi> Arthur.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Philidel. <hi>Scene, a Deep Wood.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>I left all ſafe behind;</l>
                  <l>For in the hindmoſt quarter of the Wood,</l>
                  <l>My former Lord, Grim <hi>Oſmond,</hi> walks the Round:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60031:20"/>
Calls o'er the Names, and Schools the tardy Sprights.</l>
                  <l>His Abſence gives me more ſecurity.</l>
                  <l>At every Walk I paſs'd, I drew a Spell,</l>
                  <l>So that if any Fiend, abhorring Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>There ſets his Foot, it roots him to the Ground.</l>
                  <l>Now cou'd I but diſcover <hi>Emmel ne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Task were fairly done.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>[Walking about, and Prying betwixt the Trees.]</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Grimbald <hi>ruſhing out: He ſeizes</hi> Philidel, <hi>and binds him in a Chain.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>O Rebel, have I caught thee!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah me! What hard miſhap!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>What juſt Revenge!</l>
                  <l>Thou miſcreant Elf, thou Renegado Scout,</l>
                  <l>So clean, ſo furbiſh'd, ſo renew'd in White,</l>
                  <l>The Livery of our Foes; I ſee thee through:</l>
                  <l>What mak'ſt thou here? Thou trim Apoſtate, ſpeak.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhak'ſt for Fear, I feel thy falſe Heart Pant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>All mighty <hi>Grimbald,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who would not Fear, when ſeiz'd in thy ſtrong Gripe;</l>
                  <l>But here me, Oh Renown'd, Oh worthy Fiend,</l>
                  <l>The Favourite of our Cheif.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>Away with fullſome Flattery,</l>
                  <l>The Food of Fools; thou know'ſt where laſt we met,</l>
                  <l>When but for thee, the Chriſtians had been ſwallow'd</l>
                  <l>In quaking Bogs, and Living ſent to Hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Aye, then I was ſeduc'd by <hi>Merlin</hi>'s Art,</l>
                  <l>And half perſuaded by his ſoothing Tales,</l>
                  <l>To hope for Heav'n; as if Eternal Doom</l>
                  <l>Cou'd be Revers'd, and undecreed for me:</l>
                  <l>But I am now ſet Right.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſtill thou think'ſt to fly a Fool to Mark.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>I fled from <hi>Merlin,</hi> free as Air that bore me,</l>
                  <l>T'unfold to <hi>Oſmond</hi> all his deep Deſigns.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>I believe nothing, Oh thou fond Impoſtor,</l>
                  <l>When wert thou laſt in Hell? Is not thy Name</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60031:21"/>
To <hi>Oſmond</hi> ſha'lt thou go; March, know thy Driver.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil. Kneeling.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſpare me <hi>Grimbald,</hi> and I'll be thy Slave:</l>
                  <l>Tempt Hermits for thee, in their Holy Cells,</l>
                  <l>And Virgins in their Dreams.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>Canſt thou, a Devil, hope to cheat a Devil?</l>
                  <l>A Spy; why that's a Name abhorr'd in Hell;</l>
                  <l>Haſte forward, forward, or I'll Goad thee on,</l>
                  <l>With Iron Spurrs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>But uſe me kindly then:</l>
                  <l>Pull not ſo hard, to hurt my Airy Limbs;</l>
                  <l>I'll follow thee unforc'd; look, there's thy way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay, there's the way indeed; but for more ſurety</l>
                  <l>I'll keep an Eye behind: Not one Word more,</l>
                  <l>But follow decently. Grimbald <hi>goes out, dragging</hi> Philidel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil. aſide.</speaker>
                  <l>So, catch him Spell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb. within.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh help me, help me, <hi>Philidel.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, What's the matter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, I am enſnar'd;</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns Birdlime wraps me round, and glues my Wings.</l>
                  <l>Loſe me, and I will free thee;</l>
                  <l>Do, and I'll be thy Slave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>What, to a Spy, a Name abhorr'd in Hell?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not inſult, Oh, Oh, I grow to Ground;</l>
                  <l>The Fiery Net draws cloſer on my Limbs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt not have the Eaſe to Curſe in Torments:</l>
                  <l>Be Dumb for one half Hour; ſo long my Charm</l>
                  <l>Can keep thee Silent, and there lie</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Oſmond</hi> breaks thy Chain.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Philidel <hi>unbinds his own Fetters.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter to him</hi> Merlin, <hi>with a Vial in his Hand; and</hi> Arthur.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer.</speaker>
                  <l>Well haſt thou wrought thy Safety with thy Wit,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Philidel;</hi> go Meritorious on.</l>
                  <l>Me, other Work requires, to view the Wood,</l>
                  <l>And learn to make the dire Inchantments void.</l>
                  <l>Mean time attend King <hi>Arthur</hi> in my Room;</l>
                  <l>Shew him his Love, and with theſe Soveraign Drops,</l>
                  <l>Reſtore her Sight.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Merlin <hi>giving a Viol to</hi> Philidel.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60031:21"/>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We muſt work, we muſt haſte;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Noon-Tyde Hour, is almoſt paſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sprights, that glimmer in the Sun,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Into Shades already run.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oſmond <hi>will be here, anon.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Emmeline <hi>and</hi> Matilda, <hi>at the far end of the Wood.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>O yonder, yonder ſhe's already found:</l>
                  <l>My Soul directs my ſight, and flies before it.</l>
                  <l>Now, Gentle Spirit, uſe thy utmoſt Art;</l>
                  <l>Unſeal her Eyes; and this way lead her Steps.</l>
                  <stage>Arthur <hi>withdraws behind the Scene.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Emmeline <hi>and</hi> Matilda <hi>come forward to the Front.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Philidel <hi>approaches</hi> Emmeline, <hi>ſprinkling ſome of the Water over her Eyes, out of the Vial.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus, thus I infuſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe Soveraign Dews.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fly back, ye Films, that Cloud her ſight,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And you, ye Chryſtal Humours bright,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your Noxious Vapours purg'd away,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Recover, and admit the Day.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now caſt your Eyes abroad, and ſee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All but me.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! What was that? Who ſpoke?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>I heard the Voice; 'tis one of <hi>Oſmond</hi>'s Fiends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Some bleſſed Angel ſure; I feel my Eyes</l>
                  <l>Unſeal'd, they walk abroad, and a new World</l>
                  <l>Comes ruſhing on, and ſtands all gay before me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Heavens! Oh Joy of Joys! ſhe has her ſight!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>I am new-born; I ſhall run mad for Pleaſure.
<stage>
                        <hi>Staring on</hi> Mat.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are Women ſuch as thou? Such Glorious Creatures?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60031:22"/>
                  <speaker>Arth. aſide.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh how I envy her, to be firſt ſeen!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand farther; let me take my fill of ſight.
<stage>Looking up.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>What's that above, that weakens my new Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Makes me not ſee, by ſeeing?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis the Sun.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>The Sun, 'tis ſure a God, if that be Heav'n:</l>
                  <l>Oh, if thou art a Creature, beſt and faireſt,</l>
                  <l>How well art thou, from Mortals ſo remote,</l>
                  <l>To ſhine, and not to burn, by near approach!</l>
                  <l>How haſt thou light'ned even my very Soul,</l>
                  <l>And let in Knowledge by another ſenſe!</l>
                  <l>I gaze about, new-born, to Day and thee;</l>
                  <l>A Stranger yet, an Infant of the World!</l>
                  <l>Art thou not pleas'd, <hi>Matilda?</hi> Why, like me,</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou not look and wonder?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>For theſe Sights</l>
                  <l>Are to my Eyes familiar.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em.</speaker>
                  <l>That's my Joy,</l>
                  <l>Not to have ſeen before: For Nature now,</l>
                  <l>Comes all at once, confounding my Delight.</l>
                  <l>But ah! what Thing am I? Fain wou'd I know;</l>
                  <l>Or am I blind, or do I ſee but half?</l>
                  <l>With all my Care, and looking round about,</l>
                  <l>I cannot view my Face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>None ſee themſelves</l>
                  <l>But by Reſlection; in this Glaſs you may.
<stage>Gives her a Glaſs.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm. taking the Glaſs, and looking.</speaker>
                  <l>What's this?</l>
                  <l>It holds a Face within it: Oh ſweet Face;</l>
                  <l>It draws the Mouth, and Smiles, and looksupon me;</l>
                  <l>And talks; but yet I cannot hear it Speak:</l>
                  <l>The pretty thing is Dumb.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>The pretty thing</l>
                  <l>You ſee within the Glaſs, is you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>What, Am I two? Is this another me?</l>
                  <l>Indeed it wears my Cloaths, has Hands like mine;</l>
                  <l>And Mocks what e'er I do; but that I'm ſure</l>
                  <l>I am a Maid, I'd ſwear it were my Child.
<stage>Matilda <hi>looks.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Look my <hi>Matilda;</hi> We both are in the Glaſs,</l>
                  <l>Oh, now I know it plain; they are our Names</l>
                  <l>That peep upon us there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Our Shadows, <hi>Madam.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60031:22"/>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Mine is a prettier Shaddow far, then thine.</l>
                  <l>I Love it; let me Kiſs my to'ther Self.
<stage>Kiſſing the Glaſs, and hugging it.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alas, I've kiſs'd it Dead; the fine Thing's gone;</l>
                  <l>Indeed it Kiſs'd ſo Cold, as if 'twere Dying.</l>
                  <stage>Arthur <hi>comes forward ſoftly; ſhewing himſelf behind her.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>'Tis here again.</l>
                  <l>Oh no, this Face is neither mine nor thine;</l>
                  <l>I think the Glaſs has Born another Child.
<stage>
                        <hi>She turns and ſees</hi> Arthur.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ha! What art thou with a new kind of Face,</l>
                  <l>And other Cloaths, a Noble Creature too;</l>
                  <l>But taller, bigger, fiercer in thy Look;</l>
                  <l>Of a Comptrolling Eye, Maieſtick make?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you not know him, Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Is't a Man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, And the moſt unhappy of my kind,</l>
                  <l>If you have chang'd your Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>My deareſt Lord!</l>
                  <l>Was my Soul Blind; and cou'd not that look out,</l>
                  <l>To know you, e're you Spoke? Oh Counterpart</l>
                  <l>Of our ſoft Sex; Well are ye made our Lords,</l>
                  <l>So bold, ſo great, ſo God-like are ye form'd.</l>
                  <l>How can ye Love ſuch ſilly Things as Women?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Beauty like yours Commands; and Man was made</l>
                  <l>But a more boiſterous; and a ſtronger Slave,</l>
                  <l>To you, the beſt Delights of human Kind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>But are ye mine? Is there an end of War</l>
                  <l>Are all thoſe Trumpets Dead themſelves, at laſt,</l>
                  <l>That us'd to kill Men with their Thundring Sounds?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth</speaker>
                  <l>The Sum of War is undecided yet;</l>
                  <l>And maay a breathing Body muſt be Cold,</l>
                  <l>Ere you are free.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>How came ye hither then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>By <hi>Merlin</hi>'s Art, to ſnatch a ſhort liv'd Bliſs;</l>
                  <l>To feed my famiſh'd Love upon your Eyes,</l>
                  <l>One Moment, and depart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>O Moment, worth—</l>
                  <l>Whole Ages paſt, and all that are to come!</l>
                  <l>Let Love-ſick <hi>Oſwald,</hi> now, unpitied mourn;</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Oſmond</hi> mutter Charms to Sprights in vain,</l>
                  <l>To make me love him; all ſhall not change my Soul.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60031:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60031:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60031:24"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! Does the Inchanter practice Hell upon you?</l>
                  <l>Is he my Rival too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, but I hate him;</l>
                  <l>For when he ſpoke, through my ſhut Eyes I ſaw him;</l>
                  <l>His Voice look'd ugly, and breath'd Brimſtone on me:</l>
                  <l>And then I firſt was glad that I was Blind,</l>
                  <l>Not to behold Damnation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>This time is left me to Congratulate</l>
                  <l>Your new-born Eyes; and tell you what you gain</l>
                  <l>By ſight reſtor'd, and viewing him you love.</l>
                  <l>Appear, you Airy Forms.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Airy Spirits appear in the Shapes of Men and Women.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man ſings.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh Sight, the Mother of Deſires,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What Charming Objects doſt thou yield!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis ſweet, when tedious Night expires,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſee the Roſie Morning guild</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Mountain-Tops, and paint the Field!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But, when</hi> Clorinda <hi>comes in ſight,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She makes the Summers Day more bright;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And when ſhe goes away, 'tis Night.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When Fair</hi> Clorinda <hi>comes in ſight,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom. ſings.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis ſweet the Bluſhing Morn to view;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Plains adorn'd with Pearly Dew:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But ſuch cheap Delights to ſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heaven and Nature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Give each Creature;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They have Eyes, as well as we.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This is the Joy, all Joys above,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſee, to ſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That only ſhe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That only ſhe we love!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>This is the Joy, all Joys above,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60031:24"/>
                  <speaker>Man ſings.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, if we may diſcover,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What Charms both Nymph and Lover,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis, when the Fair at Mercy lies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With Kind and Amorous Anguiſh,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To Sigh, to Look, to Languiſh,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On each others Eyes!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor. of all Men &amp; Wom.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And if we may diſcover,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Break off your Muſick; for our Foes are near.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Spirits vaniſh.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Merlin.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>My Soveraign, we have hazarded too far;</l>
                  <l>But Love excuſes you, and preſcience me.</l>
                  <l>Make haſte; for <hi>Oſmond</hi> is even now alarm'd,</l>
                  <l>And greedy of Revenge, is haſting home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh take my Love with us, or leave me here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot, for ſhe's held by Charms too ſtrong:</l>
                  <l>Which, with th' Inchanted Grove muſt be deſtroy'd;</l>
                  <l>Till when, my Art is vain: But fear not, <hi>Emmeline;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Th' Enchanter has no Pow'r on Innocence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Em.</hi> to <hi>Arth.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Farewel, Since we muſt part: When you are gone,</l>
                  <l>I'll look into my Glaſs, juſt where you look'd;</l>
                  <l>To find your Face again;</l>
                  <l>If 'tis not there, I'll think on you ſo long,</l>
                  <l>My Heart ſhall make your Picture for my Eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Where-e'er I go, my Soul ſhall ſtay with thee:</l>
                  <l>'Tis but my Shadow that I take away;</l>
                  <l>True Love is never happy but by halves;</l>
                  <l>An <hi>April</hi> Sun-ſhine, that by fits appears,</l>
                  <l>It ſmiles by Moments, but it mourns by Years.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt</hi> Arthur <hi>and</hi> Merlin <hi>at one Door.</hi>
               </stage>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60031:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60031:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60031:26"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Oſmond <hi>at the other Door, who gazes on</hi> Emmeline, <hi>and ſhe on him.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Matilda</hi> ſave me, from this ugly Thing,</l>
                  <l>This Foe to ſight, Speak, doſt thou know him:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Matil.</speaker>
                  <l>Too well; 'tis <hi>Oſwala</hi>'s Friend, the great Magician.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>It cannot be a Man, he's ſo unlike the Man I Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm. aſide.</speaker>
                  <l>Death to my Eyes, ſhe ſees!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh I cou'd not; but I'll cloſe my Sight,</l>
                  <l>And ſhut out all I can — It wo'not be;</l>
                  <l>Winking, I ſee thee ſtill, thy odious Image</l>
                  <l>Stares full into my Soul; and there infects the Room</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Arthur</hi> ſhou'd poſſeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm. aſide.</speaker>
                  <l>I find too late,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Merlin</hi> and her Lover have been here.</l>
                  <l>If I was ſir'd before, when ſhe was Blind,</l>
                  <l>Her Eyes dart Lightning now, ſhe muſt be mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>I prithee Dreadful Thing, tell me thy Buſineſs here;</l>
                  <l>And if thou canſt, Reform that odious Face;</l>
                  <l>Look not ſo Grim upon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>My Name is <hi>Oſmond,</hi> and my Buſineſs Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt a griezly look; forbidding what thou askt,</l>
                  <l>If I durſt tell thee ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>My Pent-Houſe Eye-Brows, and my Shaggy Beard</l>
                  <l>Offend your Sight, but theſe are Manly Signs;</l>
                  <l>Faint White and Red, abuſe your Expectations;</l>
                  <l>Be Woman; know your Sex, and Love full Pleaſures.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Love from a Monſter, Fiend!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>Come you muſt Love, or you muſt ſuffer Love;</l>
                  <l>No Coineſs, None, for I am Maſter here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>And when did <hi>Oſwald</hi> give away his Power,</l>
                  <l>That thou preſum'ſt to Rule? Be ſure I'll tell him:</l>
                  <l>For as I am his Priſoner, he is mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then thou art a Captive to a Captive.</l>
                  <l>O'er labour'd with the Fight, oppreſt with Thirſt;</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Oſwald</hi> whom you mention'd call'd for Drink:</l>
                  <l>I mix'd a Sleepy Potion in his Bowl;</l>
                  <l>Which he and his Fool Friend, quaff'd greedily,</l>
                  <l>The happy Doſe wrought the deſir'd effect;</l>
                  <l>Then to a Dungeons depth, I ſent both Bound:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60031:26"/>
Where ſtow'd with Snakes and Adders now they lodge,</l>
                  <l>Two Planks their Beds; Slippery with Ooſe and Slime:</l>
                  <l>The Ratts bruſh o'er their Faces with their Tails;</l>
                  <l>And croaking Paddocks crawl upon their Limbs.</l>
                  <l>Since when the Gariſon depen is on me;</l>
                  <l>Now know you are my Slave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Matil.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſtrikes a Horrour through my Blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>I Freeze, as if his impious Art had ſix'd</l>
                  <l>My Feet to Earth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>But Love ſhall thaw ye.</l>
                  <l>I'll ſhow his force in Countries cak'd with Ice,</l>
                  <l>Where the pale Pole-Star in the North of Heav'n</l>
                  <l>Sits high, and on the frory Winter broods;</l>
                  <l>Yet there Love Reigns: For proof, this Magick Wand.</l>
                  <l>Shall change the Mildneſs of ſweet <hi>Britains</hi> Clime</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Yzeland,</hi> and the fartheſt <hi>Thule</hi>'s Froſt;</l>
                  <l>Where the proud God, diſdaining Winters Bounds,</l>
                  <l>O'er leaps the Fences of Eternal Snow,</l>
                  <l>And with his Warmth, ſupplies the diſtant Sun.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Oſmond <hi>ſtrikes the Ground with his Wand: The Scene changes to a Proſpect of Winter in Frozen Countries.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Cupid <hi>Deſcends.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cup. ſings.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What ho, thou</hi> Genius <hi>of the Clime, what how</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ly'ſt thou aſleep beneath thoſe Hills of Snow?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stretch out thy Lazy Limbs; Awake, awake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Winter from thy Furry Mantle ſhake.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Genius <hi>Ariſes.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVhat Power art thou, who from below,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haſt made me Riſe, unwillingly, and ſlow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From Beds of Everlaſting Snow!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>See'ſt thou not how ſtiff, and wondrous old,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Far unfit to bear the bitter Cold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60031:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60031:27"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60031:28"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I can ſcarcely move, or draw my Breath;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let me, let me, Freeze again to Death.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou Doting Fool, forbear, forbear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVhat, Doſt thou Dream of Freezing here?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At Loves appearing, all the Skie clearing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Stormy VVinds their Fury ſpare:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVinter ſubduing, and Spring renewing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My Beams create a more Glorious Year.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou Doting Fool, forbear, forbear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVhat, Doſt thou Dream of Freezing here?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Genius.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great Love, I know thee now;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eldeſt of the Gods art Thou:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heav'n and Earth, by Thee were made.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Humane Nature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is Thy Creature,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Every where Thou art obey'd.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No part of my Dominion ſhall be waſte,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſpread my Sway, and ſing my Praiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ev'n here I will a People raiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of kind embracing Lovers, and embrac'd.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Cupid <hi>waves his Wand, upon which the Scene opens, and diſcovers a Proſpect of Ice and Snow to the end of the Stage.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Singers and Dancers, Men and Women, appears.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>See, ſee, we aſſemble,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy Revels to hold:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Though quiv'ring with Cold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We Chatter and Tremble.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60031:28"/>
                  <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis I, 'tis I, 'tis I, that have warm'd ye;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſpight of Cold Weather,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I've brought ye together:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis I, 'tis I, 'tis I, that have arm'd ye.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis Love, 'tis Love, 'tis Love that has warm'd us;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſpight of Cold Weather,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He brought us together:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis Love, 'tis Love, 'tis Love that has arm'd us.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cupid.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sound a Parley, ye Fair, and ſurrender;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Set your ſelves, and your Lovers at eaſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He's a Grateful Offender</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who Pleaſure dare ſeize:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But the Whining Pretender</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is ſure to diſpleaſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since the Fruit of Deſire is poſſeſſing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Tis Unmanly to Sigh and Complain;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VVhen we Kneel for Redreſſing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VVe move your Diſdain:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Love was made for a Bleſſing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And not for a Pain.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>A Dance; after which the Singers and Dancers depart.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>I cou'd be pleas'd with any one but thee,</l>
                  <l>Who entertain'd my ſight with ſuch Gay Shows,</l>
                  <l>As Men and Women moving here and there;</l>
                  <l>That Courſing one another in their Steps,</l>
                  <l>Have made their Feet a Tune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60031:29"/>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>What, Coying it again!</l>
                  <l>No more; but make me happy to my Guſt,</l>
                  <l>That is, without your ſtruggling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>From my ſight,</l>
                  <l>Thou all thy Devils in one, thou dar'ſt not force me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>You teach me well, I find you wou'd be Raviſh'd;</l>
                  <l>I'll give you that excuſe your Sex deſires.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He begins to lay hold on her, and they ſtruggle.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb. within.</speaker>
                  <l>O help me, Maſter, help me!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that, my <hi>Grimbald!</hi> Come and help thou me:</l>
                  <l>For 'tis thy Work t'aſſiſt a Raviſher.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb. within.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot ſtir; I am Spell-caught by <hi>Philidel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And purs'd within a Net. With a huge heavy weight of Holy Words,</l>
                  <l>Laid on my Head; that keeps me down from riſing</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll read 'em backwards, and releaſe thy Bonds:</l>
                  <l>Mean time go in: —
<stage>To Emmeline.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prepare your ſelf, and eaſe my Drudgery:</l>
                  <l>But if you will not fairly be enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>A little honeſt Force, is well employ'd.
<stage>Exit Oſmond.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Heav'n be my Guard, I have no other Friend!</l>
                  <l>Heav'n ever preſent to thy Suppliants Aid,</l>
                  <l>Protect and pity Innocence betray'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt</hi> Emmeline <hi>and</hi> Matilda.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60031:29"/>
               <head>ACT IV. SCENE I.</head>
               <stage>Enter Oſmond Solus.</stage>
               <l>NOw I am ſettled in my Force-full Sway;</l>
               <l>Why then, I'll be Luxurious in my Love;</l>
               <l>Take my full Guſt, and ſetting Forms aſide,</l>
               <l>I'll bid the Slave, that fires my Blood, lie down.</l>
               <stage>Seems to be going off.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Grimbald, <hi>who meets him.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſo faſt, Maſter, Danger threatens thee:</l>
                  <l>There's a black Cloud, deſcending from above,</l>
                  <l>Full of Heavens Venom, burſting o'er thy Head.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>Malicious Fiend, thou ly'ſt: For I am fenc'd</l>
                  <l>By Millions of thy Fellows, in my Grove:</l>
                  <l>I bad thee, when I freed thee from the Charm,</l>
                  <l>Run ſcouting through the Wood, from Tree to Tree,</l>
                  <l>And look if all my Devils were on Duty:</l>
                  <l>Hadſt thou perform'd thy Charge, thou tardy Spright,</l>
                  <l>Thou wouldſt have known no Danger threatn'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>When did a Devil fail in Diligence?</l>
                  <l>Poor Mortal, thou thy ſelf art overſeen;</l>
                  <l>I have been there, and thence I bring this News.</l>
                  <l>Thy Fatal Foe, great <hi>Arthur,</hi> is at hand;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Merlin</hi> has ta'en his time while thou wert abſent,</l>
                  <l>T' obſerve thy Characters, their Force, and Nature,</l>
                  <l>And Counterwork thy Spells.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſmo.</speaker>
                  <l>The Devil take <hi>Merlin;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'll caſt 'em all anew, and inſtantly,</l>
                  <l>All of another Mould; be thou at hand.</l>
                  <l>Their Compoſition was, before, of Horror;</l>
                  <l>Now they ſhall be of Blandiſhment, and Love;</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60031:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60031:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:60031:31"/>
                  <l>Seducing Hopes, ſoft Pity, tender Moans:</l>
                  <l>Art ſhall meet Art; and, when they think to win,</l>
                  <l>The Fools ſhall find their Labour to begin.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt</hi> Oſm. <hi>and</hi> Grimb.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Arthur, <hi>and</hi> Merlin <hi>at another Door.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Scene of the Wood continues.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus far it is permitted me to go;</l>
                  <l>But all beyond this Spot, is fenc'd with Charms;</l>
                  <l>I may no more; but only with advice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>My Sword ſhall do the reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>Remember well, that all is but Illuſion;</l>
                  <l>Go on; good Stars attend thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Doubt me not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet in prevention</l>
                  <l>Of what may come, I'll leave my <hi>Philidel</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To watch thy Steps, and with him leave my Wand;</l>
                  <l>The touch of which, no Earthy Fiend can bear,</l>
                  <l>In whate'er Shape transform'd, but muſt lay down</l>
                  <l>His borrow'd Figure, and confeſs the Devil.</l>
                  <l>Once more Farewel, and proſper.
<stage>Exit Merlin.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth. walking.</speaker>
                  <l>No Danger yet, I ſee no Walls of Fire,</l>
                  <l>No City of the Fiends, with Forms obſcene,</l>
                  <l>To grin from far, on Flaming Battlements.</l>
                  <l>This is indeed the Grove I ſhou'd deſtroy;</l>
                  <l>But where's the Horrour? Sure the Prophet err'd.</l>
                  <l>Hark! Muſick, and the warbling Notes of Birds;
<stage>Soft Muſick.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hell entertains me, like ſome welcom Gueſt.</l>
                  <l>More Wonders yet; yet all delightful too,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Silver Current to forbid my paſſage,</l>
                  <l>And yet to invite me, ſtands a Golden Bridge:</l>
                  <l>Perhaps a Trap, for my Unwary Feet</l>
                  <l>To ſink, and whelm me underneath the Waves;</l>
                  <l>With Fire or Water, let him wage his VVar,</l>
                  <l>Or all the Elements at once; I'll on.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>As he is going to the Bridge, two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Water; They ſhew themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60031:31"/>
                  <l>
                     <stage>1 Syren.</stage> 
                     <hi>O paſs not on, but ſtay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And waſte the Joyous Day</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVith us in gentle Play:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Unbend to Love, unbend thee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O lay thy Sword aſide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And other Arms provide;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For other Wars attend thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſweeter to be try'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Chor.</stage> 
                     <hi>For other Wars,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Both ſing.</stage> 
                     <hi>Two Daughters of this Aged Stream are we;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And both our Sea-green Locks have comb'd for thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come Bathe with us an Hour or two,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come Naked in, for we are ſo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What Danger from a Naked Foe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come Bathe with us, come Bathe, and ſhare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVhat Pleaſures in the Floods appear;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We'll beat the Waters till they bound,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Circle, round, around, around,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Circle round, around.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Lazie Pleaſure trickles through my Veins;</l>
                  <l>Here cou'd I ſtay, and well be Couzen'd here.</l>
                  <l>But Honour calls; Is Honour in ſuch haſte?</l>
                  <l>Can he not Bait at ſuch a pleaſing Inn?</l>
                  <l>No; for the more I look, the more I long;</l>
                  <l>Farewel, ye Fair Illuſions, I muſt leave ye,</l>
                  <l>While I have Power to ſay, that I muſt leave ye.</l>
                  <l>Farewel, with half my Soul I ſtagger off;</l>
                  <l>How dear this ſlying Victory has coſt,</l>
                  <l>When, if I ſtay to ſtruggle, I am loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>As he is going forward,</hi> Nymphs <hi>and</hi> Sylvans <hi>come cut from behind the Trees. Baſe and two Trebles ſing the following Song to a</hi> Minuet.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60031:32"/>
                  <hi>Dance with the Song, all with Branches in their Hands.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <l>
                     <stage>Song.</stage> 
                     <hi>How happy the Lover,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How eaſie his Chain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How pleaſing his Pain?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How ſweet to diſcover!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He ſighs not in vain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For Love every Creature</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is form'd by his Nature;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No Joys are above</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Pleaſures of Love.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The Dance continues with the ſame Meaſure play'd alone.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In vain are our Graces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In vain are your Eyes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If Love you deſpiſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When Age furrows Faces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis time to be wiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then uſe the ſhort Bleſſing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That Flies in Poſſeſſing:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No Joys are above</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Pleaſures of Love.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>And what are theſe Fantaſtick Fairy Joys,</l>
                  <l>To Love like mine? Falſe Joys, falſe Welcomes all.</l>
                  <l>Begone, ye <hi>Sylvan</hi> Trippers of the Green;</l>
                  <l>Fly after Night, and overtake the Moon.
<stage>Here the Dancers, Singers and Syrens vaniſh.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>This goodly Tree ſeems Queen of all the Grove.</l>
                  <l>The Ringlets round her Trunk declare her guilty</l>
                  <l>Of many Midnight-Sabbaths Revell'd here.</l>
                  <l>Her will I firſt attempt.
<stage>Arthur <hi>ſtrikes at the Tree, and cuts it; Blood ſpouts out of it, a Groan follows, then a Shreik.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Good Heav'ns, what Monſtrous Prodigies are theſe!</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60031:32"/>
Blood follows from my blow; the wounded Rind</l>
                  <l>Spouts on my Sword, and Sanguine dyes the Plain.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>He ſtrtkes again: A Voice of</hi> Emmeline <hi>from behind.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Em. from behind.</speaker>
                  <l>Forbear, if thou haſt Pity, ah, forbear!</l>
                  <l>Theſe Groans proceed not from a Senceleſs Plant,</l>
                  <l>No Spouts of Blood run welling from a Tree.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak what thou art; I charge thee ſpeak thy Being;</l>
                  <l>Thou that haſt made my curdl'd Blood run back,</l>
                  <l>My Heart heave up; my Hair to riſe in Briſtles,</l>
                  <l>And ſcarcely left a Voice to ask thy Name.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Emmeline <hi>breaks out of the Tree ſhewing her Arm Bloody.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Whom thou haſt hurt, Unkind and Cruel ſee;</l>
                  <l>Look on this Blood, 'tis fatal, ſtill, to me</l>
                  <l>To bear thy Wounds, my Heart has felt 'em firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſhe; Amazement roots me to the Ground!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>By cruel Charms, dragg'd from my peaceful Bower,</l>
                  <l>Fierce <hi>Oſmond</hi> cloſs'd me in this bleeding Bark;</l>
                  <l>And bid me ſtand expos'd to the bleak Winds,</l>
                  <l>And Winter Storms; and Heav'ns Inclemency,</l>
                  <l>Bound to the Fate of this Hell-haunted Grove;</l>
                  <l>So that whatever Sword, or ſounding Axe,</l>
                  <l>Shall violate this Plant, muſt pierce my Fleſh,</l>
                  <l>And when that falls. I dye.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>If this be true,</l>
                  <l>O never, never, to be ended Charm,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt by me; yet all my be Illuſion.</l>
                  <l>Break up, ye thickning Foggs, and filmy Miſts,</l>
                  <l>All that be-lye my Sight, and cheat my Serſe.</l>
                  <l>For Reaſon ſtill pronounces, 'tis not ſhe,</l>
                  <l>And thus reſolv'd—
<stage>Lifts up his Sword, is going to ſtrike.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Do, ſtrike <hi>Barbarian,</hi> ſtrike;</l>
                  <l>And ſtrew my mangl'd Limbs, with every ſtroke</l>
                  <l>Wound me, and double kill me, with Unkindneſs,</l>
                  <l>That by thy Hand I ſell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I do, ye Powers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Lay down thy Vengeful Sword; 'tis fatal here:</l>
                  <l>What need of Arms, where no Defence is made?</l>
                  <l>A Love-Sick Virgin, panting with Deſire</l>
                  <l>No Conſcious Eye t'intrude on our Delights:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60031:33"/>
For this thou haſt the <hi>Syren</hi>'s Songs deſpis'd;</l>
                  <l>For this, thy Faithful Paſſion I Reward;</l>
                  <l>Haſte then, to take me longing to thy Arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>O Love! O <hi>Merlin!</hi> Whom ſhould I believe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>Believe thy Self, thy Youth, thy Love, and me;</l>
                  <l>They only, they, who pleaſe themſelves are Wiſe:</l>
                  <l>Diſarm thy Hand, that mine may meet it bare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>By thy leave, Reaſon, here I throw thee off,</l>
                  <l>Thou load of Life: If thou wert made for Souls,</l>
                  <l>Then Souls ſhou'd have been made without their Bodies.</l>
                  <l>If, falling for the firſt Created Fair,</l>
                  <l>Was <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fault, great Grandſire I forgive thee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eden</hi> was loſt, as all thy Sons wou'd looſe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Going towards</hi> Emmeline, <hi>and pulling off his Gantlet.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Philidel <hi>running.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, poor deluded Mortal, hold thy Hand;</l>
                  <l>Which if thou giv'ſt, is plighted to a Feind.</l>
                  <l>For Proof, behold the Virtue of this Wand;</l>
                  <l>Th' Infernal Paint ſhall vaniſh from her Face,</l>
                  <l>And Hell ſhall ſtand Reveal'd.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Strikes</hi> Emmeline <hi>with a Wand, who ſtraight deſcends:</hi> Philidel <hi>runs to the Deſcent, and pulls up</hi> Grimbald, <hi>and binds him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Now ſee to whoſe Embraces thou wert falling.</l>
                  <l>Behold the Maiden Modeſty of <hi>Grimbald,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The groſſeſt, earthieſt, uglieſt Fiend in Hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Horrour ſeizes me,</l>
                  <l>To think what Headlong Ruine I have tempted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſte to thy Work; a Noble ſtroke or two</l>
                  <l>Ends all the Charms, and diſenchants the Grove.</l>
                  <l>I'll hold thy Miſtreſs bound.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Then here's for Earneſt;</l>
                  <stage>Strikes twice or thrice, and the Tree falls, or ſinks: A Peal of Thunder immediately follows, with dreadful Howlings.</stage>
                  <l>'Tis ſiniſh'd, and the Dusk that yet remains,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60031:33"/>
Is but the Native Horrour of the Wood.</l>
                  <l>But I muſt loſe no time; the Paſs is free;</l>
                  <l>Th' unrooſted Fiends have quitted this Abode;</l>
                  <l>On you proud Towers, before the day be done,</l>
                  <l>My glittering Banners ſhall be wav'd againſt the ſetting Sun.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Arthur.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Come on my ſurly Slave; come ſtalk along,</l>
                  <l>And ſtamp a mad-Mans pace, and drag thy Chain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grimb.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll Champ and Foam upon 't, till the blue Venom</l>
                  <l>Work upward to thy Hands, and looſe their hold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>Know'ſt thou this powerful Wand; 'tis lifted up;</l>
                  <l>A ſecond ſtroke wou'd ſend thee to the Centre,</l>
                  <l>Benum'd and Dead, as far as Souls can Die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
                  <l>I wou'd thou woud'ſt, to rid me of my Senſe:</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be whoop'd through Hell at my return,</l>
                  <l>Inglorious from the Miſchief I deſign'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>And therefore ſince thou loath'ſt Etherial Light,</l>
                  <l>The Morning Sun ſhall beat on thy black Brows;</l>
                  <l>The Breath thou draw'ſt ſhall be of opper Air,</l>
                  <l>Hoſtile to thee; and to thy Earthy make,</l>
                  <l>So light, ſo thin, that thou ſha't Starve, for want</l>
                  <l>Of thy groſs Food, till gaſping thou ſhalt lie,</l>
                  <l>And blow it back, all Sooty to the Sky.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>exit</hi> Philidel, <hi>dragging</hi> Grimbald <hi>after him.</hi>
               </stage>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60031:34"/>
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Oſmond <hi>as affrighted.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>GRimbald</hi> made Priſoner, and my Grove deſtroy'd!</l>
                  <l>Now what can ſave me — Hark the Drums and Trumpets!</l>
                  <stage>Drums and Trumpets within.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Arthur</hi> is marching onward to the Fort,</l>
                  <l>I have but one Recourſe, and that's to <hi>Oſwald;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But will he Fight for me, whom I have injur'd?</l>
                  <l>No, not for me, but for himſelf he muſt;</l>
                  <l>I'll urge him with the laſt Neceſſity;</l>
                  <l>Better give up my Miſtreſs than my Life.</l>
                  <l>His force is much unequal to his Rival;</l>
                  <l>True; — But I'll help him with my utmoſt Art,</l>
                  <l>And try t' unravel Fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exit</hi> Oſmond.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Arthur, Conon, Aurelius, Albanact, <hi>and Soldiers.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Now there remains but this one Labour more;</l>
                  <l>And if we have the Hearts of true Born <hi>Britains,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The forcing of that Caſtle Crowns the Day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aurel.</speaker>
                  <l>The Works are weak, the Gariſon but thin,</l>
                  <l>Diſpirited with frequent Overthrows,</l>
                  <l>Already wavering on their ill mann'd Walls.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alban.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſhift their places oft, and ſculk from War,</l>
                  <l>Sure Signs of pale Deſpair, and eaſie Rout;</l>
                  <l>It ſhews they place their Confidence in Magick,</l>
                  <l>And when their Devils fail, their Hearts are Dead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Then, where you ſee'em cluſt'ring moſt, in Motion,</l>
                  <l>And ſtaggering in their Ranks, there preſs 'em home;</l>
                  <l>For that 's a Coward heap— How's this, a Sally?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60031:34"/>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Oſwald, Guillamar, <hi>and Soldiers on the other ſide.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>Beyond my Hopes, to meet 'em on the ſquare.</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſw. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing.</speaker>
                  <l>Brave <hi>Britains</hi> hold; and thou their famous Chief</l>
                  <l>Attend what <hi>Saxon Oſwald</hi> will propoſe.</l>
                  <l>He owns your Victory; but whether owing</l>
                  <l>To Valour, or to Fortune, that he doubts.</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Arthur</hi> dares aſcribe it to the firſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſingl'd from a Crowd, will tempt a Conqueſt,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Oſwald</hi> Offers, let our Troops retire,</l>
                  <l>And Hand to Hand, let us decide our Striſe:</l>
                  <l>This if Refus'd, bear Witneſs Earth and Heaven,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſteal'ſt a Crown and Miſtreſs undeſerv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll not Uſurp thy Title of a Robber,</l>
                  <l>Nor will upbraid thee, that before I proffer'd</l>
                  <l>This ſingle Combat, which thou didſt avoid;</l>
                  <l>So glad I am, on any Terms to meet thee,</l>
                  <l>And not diſcourage thy Repenting ſhame;</l>
                  <l>As once <hi>Eneas</hi> my Fam'd Anceſtor,</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the <hi>Trojan</hi> and <hi>Rutilian</hi> Bands,</l>
                  <l>Fought for a Crown, and bright <hi>Lavinia</hi>'s Bed,</l>
                  <l>So will I meet thee, Hand to Hand oppos'd:</l>
                  <l>My Auguring Mind, aſſures the ſame Succeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To his Men.</speaker>
                  <l>Hence out of view; If I am Slain, or yield,</l>
                  <l>Renounce me Britains for a Recreant Knight,</l>
                  <l>And let the Saxon peacefully enjoy</l>
                  <l>His former footing in our famous Iſle.</l>
                  <l>To Ratifie theſe Terms, I ſwear—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſw.</speaker>
                  <l>You need not;</l>
                  <l>Your Honour is of Force, without your Oath.</l>
                  <l>I only add, that if I fall, or yeild,</l>
                  <l>Yours be the Crown, and <hi>Emmeline.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>That's two Crowns.</l>
                  <l>No more; we keep the looking Heav'ns and Sun</l>
                  <l>Too long in Expectation of our Arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Both Armies go clear off the Stage.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60031:35"/>
                  <hi>They Fight with Spunges in their Hands, dipt in Blood; after ſome equal Paſſes and Cloſeing, they appear both Wounded:</hi> Arthur <hi>Stumbles among the Trees,</hi> Oſwald <hi>falls over him, they both Riſe;</hi> Arthur <hi>Wounds him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, then</hi> Oſwald <hi>Retreats. Enter</hi> Oſmond <hi>from among the Trees, and with his Wand, ſtrikes</hi> Arthur<hi>'s Sword out of his Hand, and</hi> Exit. Oſwald <hi>purſues</hi> Arthur. Merlin <hi>enters, and gives</hi> Arthur <hi>his Sword, and</hi> Exit, <hi>they cloſe, and</hi> Arthur <hi>in the fall, diſarms</hi> Oſwald.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Conſeſs thy felf o'ercome, and ask thy Life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not worth asking, when 'tis in thy Power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Then take it as my Gift.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſwa.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> wretched Gift.</l>
                  <l>With loſs of Empire, Liberty, and Love.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>A Conſort of Trumpets within, proclaiming</hi> Arthur<hi>'s Victory, while they Sound,</hi> Arthur <hi>and</hi> Oſwal. <hi>ſeem to Confer.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>'Tis too much Bounty to a vanquiſh'd Foe;</l>
                  <l>Yet not enough to make me Fortunate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Life, thy Liberty, thy Honour Safe,</l>
                  <l>Lead back thy Saxons to their Antient Elb:</l>
                  <l>I wou'd Reſtore thee fruitful <hi>Kent,</hi> the Gift</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Vortigern</hi> for <hi>Hengiſt</hi>'s ill bought aid,</l>
                  <l>But that my <hi>Britain</hi>'s brook no Foreign Power,</l>
                  <l>To Lord it in a Land, Sacred to Freedom;</l>
                  <l>And of its Rights, Tenacious to the laſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſw.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor more then thou haſt offer'd wou'd I take.</l>
                  <l>I would Refuſe all <hi>Britain,</hi> held in Homage;</l>
                  <l>And own no other Maſters but the Gods.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter on one ſide;</hi> Merlin, Emmeline, <hi>and</hi> Matilda. Conon, Aurelius, Albanact, <hi>with Britiſh Soldiers, bearing King</hi> Arthur<hi>'s Standard diſplay'd.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>On the other ſide,</hi> Guillamar <hi>and</hi> Oſinond, <hi>with Saxon Soldiers, dragging their Colours on the Ground.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Art. going to Emm. and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing her</stage>
               <l>At length, at length, I have thee in my Arms,</l>
               <l>Tho' our Malevolent Stars have ſtrugled hard,</l>
               <l>And held us long aſunder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60031:35"/>
                  <speaker>Emm.</speaker>
                  <l>We are ſo fitted for each other Hearts,</l>
                  <l>That Heav'n had err'd, in making of a third,</l>
                  <l>To get betwixt, and intercept our Loves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſw.</speaker>
                  <l>Were there but this, this only ſight to ſee,</l>
                  <l>The price of <hi>Britain</hi> ſhou'd not buy my ſtay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
                  <l>Take hence that Monſter of Ingratitude,</l>
                  <l>Him, who betray'd his Maſter, bear him hence,</l>
                  <l>And in that loathſom Dungeon plunge him deep,</l>
                  <l>Where he plung'd Noble <hi>Oſwald.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oſm.</speaker>
                  <l>That indeed is fitteſt for me,</l>
                  <l>For there I ſhall be near my Kindred Fiends,</l>
                  <l>And ſpare my <hi>Grimbald</hi>'s Pains to bear me to 'em.
<stage>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> carried off.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mer. to Arth.</speaker>
                  <l>For this Days Palm, and for thy former Acts,</l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Britain</hi> freed, and Foreign Force expell'd,</l>
                  <l>Thou, <hi>Arthur,</hi> haſt acquir'd a future Fame,</l>
                  <l>And of three Chriſtian Worthies, art the firſt:</l>
                  <l>And now at once, to treat thy Sight and Soul,</l>
                  <l>Behold what Rouling Ages ſhall produce:</l>
                  <l>The Wealth, the Loves, the Glories of our Iſle,</l>
                  <l>Which yet like Golden Oar, Unripe in Beds,</l>
                  <l>Expect the Warm Indulgency of Heav'n</l>
                  <l>To call 'em forth to Light—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>To Oſw.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor thou, brave Saxon Prince, diſdain our Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs;</l>
                  <l>Britains and Saxons ſhall be once one People;</l>
                  <l>One Common Tongue, one Common Faith ſhall bind</l>
                  <l>Our Jarring Bands, in a perpetual Peace.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Merlin <hi>waves his Wand; the Scene changes, and diſcovers the Britiſh Ocean in a Storm.</hi> Aeolus <hi>in a Cloud above: Four Winds hanging,</hi> &amp;c.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aeolus. ſinging.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ye Bluſt'ring Brethren of the Skies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe Breath has ruffl'd all the Watry Plain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Retire, and let</hi> Britannia <hi>Riſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Triumph o'er the Main.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Serene and Calm, and void of fear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Queen of Iſlands muſt appear:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Serene and Calm, as when the Spring</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The New-Created World began,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60031:36"/>
                     <hi>And Birds on Boughs did ſoftly ſing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their Peaceful Homage paid to Man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>While</hi> Eurus <hi>did his Blaſts forbear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In favour of the Tender Year.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Retreat, Rude Winds, Retreat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To Hollow Rocks, your Stormy Seat;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There ſwell your Lungs, and vainly, vainly threat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Aeolus <hi>aſcends, and the four Winds fly off. The Scene opens, and diſcovers a calm Sea, to the end of the Houſe. An</hi> Iſland <hi>ariſes, to a ſoft Tune;</hi> Britannia <hi>ſeated in the</hi> Iſland, <hi>with Fiſhermen at her Feet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Tune changes; the Fiſhermen come aſhore, and Dance a while; After which,</hi> Pan <hi>and a</hi> Nereide <hi>come on the Stage, and ſing.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Pan <hi>and</hi> Nereide <hi>Sings.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Round thy Coaſts, Fair Nymph of</hi> Britain,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For thy Guard our Waters flow:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Proteus <hi>all his Herd admitting,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>On thy Greens to Graze below.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Foreign Lands thy Fiſhes Taſting,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Learn from thee Luxurious Faſting.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Song of three Parts.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For Folded Flocks, on Fruitful Plains,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Shepherds and the Farmers Gains,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fair</hi> Britain <hi>all the VVorld outvyes;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Pan, <hi>as in</hi> Arcadia <hi>Reigns,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VVhere Pleaſure mixt with Profit lyes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though</hi> Jaſons <hi>Office was Fam'd of old,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Britiſh <hi>VVool is growing Gold;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60031:36"/>
                        <hi>No Mines can more of VVealth ſupply;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It keeps the Peaſant from the Cold,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And takes for Kings the</hi> Tyrian <hi>Dye.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <p>The laſt <hi>Stanza</hi> ſung over again betwixt <hi>Pan</hi> and the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reide.</hi> After which the former Dance is varied, and goes on.</p>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Comus <hi>with three Peaſants, who ſing the following Song in Parts.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Com.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>YOur Hay it is Mow'd, &amp; your Corn is Reap'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your Barns will be full, and your Hovels heap'd;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come, my Boys, come;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come, my Boys, come;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And merrily Roar out Harveſt Home;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Harveſt Home,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Harveſt Home;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And merrily Roar out Harveſt Home.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come, my Boys, come,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Man.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>VVe ha' cheated the Parſon, we'll cheat him agen;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For why ſhou'd a Blockhead ha' One in Ten?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One in Ten,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One in Ten.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For why ſhou'd a Blockhead ha' One in Ten?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One in Ten,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One in Ten;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For why ſhou'd a Blockhead ha' One in Ten?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For Prating ſo long like a Book-learn'd Sot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till Pudding and Dumplin burn to Pot;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Burn to Pot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Burn to Pot;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till Fudding and Dumplin burn to Pot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Burn to Pot,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60031:37"/>
                  <speaker>3.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We'll toſs off our Ale till we canno' ſtand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Hoigh for the Honour of Old</hi> England:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Old</hi> England,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Old</hi> England;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And Hoigh for the Honour of Old</hi> England.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Old</hi> England, &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The Dance vary'd into a round Country-Dance.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Venus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Venus.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Faireſt Iſle, all Iſles Excelling,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Seat of Pleaſures, and of Loves;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Venus <hi>here, will chuſe her Dwelling,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And forſake her</hi> Cyprian <hi>Groves.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>Cupid, <hi>from his Fav'rite Nation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Care and Envy will Remove;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jealouſie, that poyſons Paſſion,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Deſpair that dies for Love.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gentle Murmurs, ſweet Complaining,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sighs that blow the Fire of Love;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Soft Repulſes, kind Diſdaining,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall be all the Pains you prove.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Every Swain ſhall pay his Duty,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Grateful every Nymph ſhall prove;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And as theſe Excel in Beauty,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thoſe ſhall be Renown'd for Love.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60031:37"/>
            <head>SONG by Mr. <hi>HOWE.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>She.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>YOu ſay, 'Tis Love Creates the Pain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of which ſo ſadly you Complain;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And yet wou'd fain Engage my Heart</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In that uneaſie cruel part:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But how, Alas! think you, that I,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Can bear the Wound of which you die.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis not my Paſſion makes my Care,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But your Indiff'rence gives Deſpair:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Luſty Sun begets no Spring,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till Gentle Show'rs Aſſiſtance bring:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So Love that Scorches, and Deſtroys,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Till Kindneſs Aids, can cauſe no Joys.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>She.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Love has a Thouſand Ways to pleaſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But more to rob us of our Eaſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For Wakeful Nights, and Careful Days,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some Hours of Pleaſure he repays;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But Abſence ſoon, or Jealous Fears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O'erflow the Joys with Floods of Tears.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:60031:38"/>
               <speaker>He.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By vain and ſenſeleſs Forms betray'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Harmleſs Love's th' Offender made;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>While we no other Pains endure,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Than thoſe, that we our ſelves procure:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But one ſoft Moment makes Amends</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For all the Torment that attends.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>5. Chorus of Both.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let us love, let us love, and to Happineſs haſte;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Age and Wiſdom come too faſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Youth for Loving was deſign'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He alone. <hi>I'll be conſtant, you be kind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She alone. <hi>You be conſtant, I'll be kind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both. <hi>Heav'n can give no greater Bleſſing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Than faithful Love, and kind Poſſeſſing.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <stage>After the Dialogue, a Warlike Conſort: The Scene opens above, and diſcovers the Order of the Garter.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Honour, <hi>Attended by</hi> Hero's.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Merl.</speaker>
               <l>Theſe who laſt enter'd, are our Valiant <hi>Britains,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſhall by Sea and Land Repel our Foes.</l>
               <l>Now look above, and in Heav'ns High Abyſs,</l>
               <l>Behold what Fame attends thoſe future Hero's.</l>
               <l>Honour, who leads 'em to that Steepy Height,</l>
               <l>In her Immortal Song, ſhall tell the reſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60031:38"/>
(Honour ſings.)</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hon.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>St.</hi> George, <hi>the Patron of our Iſle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Soldier, and a Saint,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On that Auſpicious Order ſmile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which Love and Arms will plant.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Natives not alone appear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Court this Martiall Prize;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But Foreign Kings, Adopted here,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Crowns at Home deſpiſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Soveraign High, in Aweful State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Honours ſhall beſtow;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſee his Sceptr'd Subjects wait</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>On his Commands below.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <stage>A full Chorus of the whole Song: After which the Grand Dance.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arth. to Merl.</speaker>
               <l>Wiſely you have, whate'er will pleaſe, reveal'd,</l>
               <l>What wou'd diſpleaſe, as wiſely have conceal'd:</l>
               <l>Triumphs of War and Peace, at full ye ſhow,</l>
               <l>But ſwiftly turn the Pages of our Wo.</l>
               <l>Reſt we contented with our preſent State;</l>
               <l>'Tis Anxious to enquire of future Fate.</l>
               <l>That Race of Hero's is enough alone</l>
               <l>For all unſeen Diſaſters to atone.</l>
               <l>Let us make haſte betimes to Reap our ſhare,</l>
               <l>And not Reſign them all the Praiſe of War.</l>
               <l>But ſet th' Example; and their Souls Inflame,</l>
               <l>To Copy out their Great Forefathers Fame.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
